<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine discouerie of ten English lepers, verie noisome and hurtfull to the Church and common wealth setting before our eies the iniquitie of these latter dayes, and inducing vs to a due consideration of our selues. Published by Thomas Timme minister.</title>
            <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118801</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854008</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854008</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14108)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 340:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine discouerie of ten English lepers, verie noisome and hurtfull to the Church and common wealth setting before our eies the iniquitie of these latter dayes, and inducing vs to a due consideration of our selues. Published by Thomas Timme minister.</title>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short, dwelling vpon Bredstreet hill, neere the end of old Fishstreet at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An attack on schismatics, church robbers, etc.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discouerie of ten English lepers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:1"/>
            <p>A PLAINE DISCO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of ten Engliſh Lepers, verie noiſome and hurtfull to the Church and common wealth: Setting before our eies the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theſe latter dayes, and inducing vs to a due conſideration of our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by THOMAS TIMME <hi>Minister.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Peter Short, dwelling vpon Bredstreet hill, neere the end of old Fiſhſtreet at the ſigne of the Starre. 1592.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:2"/>
            <head>To the right honourable his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>good Lorde Sir William Brooke</hi> knight, Baron of Cobham, Lord warden of <hi>the cinque ports, knight of the Garter, and one of</hi> her Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſell, Thomas Timme his humble ſeruant, wiſheth long life, and eternall felicitie in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He woondring</hi> Queene of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> (right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) preſented the moſt wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> with the golde of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyr,</hi> &amp; richeſt gifts of the land. The <hi>Samnites</hi> brought with them a greate maſſ of treaſure for the noble Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Marcus Craſſus.</hi> Howe preposterous then may I ſeeme, which preſume to bring into your honourable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence <hi>Lernam malorum,</hi> as it were a lazary of Leapers? Pardon (right Honourable) my rudeneſſe herein, and take it well in woorth, though it may of ſome be reputed
<pb facs="tcp:19414:3"/>
               <hi>Calabrihoſpitis munus,</hi> a trifling gift. Things which haue a baſe and rude forme, not bombaſted to pleaſe the fantaſie, ſomtimes affoord more profit then is expected. Happily this home-ſpunne webbe may be profitable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and therein acceptable to your Honour, a principall piller of common wealth. For as the ſoule is much more excellent then the bodie, ſo whatſoeuer tendeth to the good thereof, is farre more precious then golde, and to be preferred, before all bodily and earthly treaſure. But a ſecret and hidden maladie, ſuch as is ſinne, the ſickeneſſe of the ſoule, the decay of men, the ouerthrow of Nations, and the ruine of the whole worlde, can neuer be well cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reformed, except firſt diſcouered. For which cauſe, ten capitall ſinnes are in this Catalogue detected, being as forcible to bring this noble Realme of England to thraule, as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ten brethren were to ſell him into the captiuitie of Aegypt: in the which men in this age are gone backeward from God, ten degrees further then the ſhadow of <hi>Ahaz</hi> diall out of courſe:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.3.</note> ſo as if they doe not ſpedily repent, and ſequeſter theſe ten, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did his ten polluted concubines, they will be vnto vs as ten women,<note place="margin">Leui. 26.26</note> that ſhall bake our bread in the ouen of ſcarcitie, and deliuer the ſame to vs by waight: And at the laſt God will ſay vnto vs,<note place="margin">Num. 14.22.</note> as he ſaid to the Iſraelites. <hi>This people that haue tempted me with theſe ten tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhal not ſee the land of promiſe.</hi> Therfore (right Honourable) as <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> temple in the city <hi>Epidau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> in <hi>Grece,</hi> was to all maner diſeaſed perſons which reſorted thither a meane to recouer deſired health, (ſuch medicines as would cure their maladics being there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto them:) ſo the generall good which I wiſh all to find in the diſcouerie of theſe ten ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon euils, (that not ſo fewe as ten righteous perſons, for the which God would haueſpared <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> might bee
<pb facs="tcp:19414:3"/>found among vs) hath moued me, though after a plaine and rude ſort, to publiſh the ſame. For as of ten tribes one remained ſtill to the houſe of Dauid: and of ten Lepers one became a faithfull conuert: and of ten virgins, fiue were wiſe, and waited for the comming of Christ: ſo in this euil generation, God will (I doubt not) reſerue to him ſelfe a remnant which ſhall keepe themſelues and their garments vnſpotted of the world. Further, your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vertues ſhadowed with no cloudes of vice, and of your wiſdome correſpondent to your place, hath mooued me to preſent this to your Lordſhips hands: yet, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare to aduenture ſo baſe a gift to ſo worthie a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage. But the late experience of your honourable cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, hath imboldened me to make it a meſſenger of my dutie and vnfained loue towards you. May it pleaſe your honour to accept it, I cannot but reuerently acknowledge that it proceedeth more of your noble minde, then of the worthineſſe of the gift: and in regard thereof, holde my ſelfe ſo much the more bounde in all Christian dutie to your honour during life. Thus beſeeching almightie God to bleſſe your Honour, I wiſh to the world, the loue of God the father, an vniuer ſall peace at the laſt to his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church, confuſion of all hypocrites, and to all his choſen people euerlasting life in the kingdome of heauen. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble ſeruant</hi> Thomas Timme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:4"/>
            <head>The Contents of this <hi>Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt Leper, is the Schiſmatique.</item>
               <item>The ſeconde Leper, is the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robber.</item>
               <item>The third Leper is the Simoniac.</item>
               <item>The fourth Leper, is the Hypocrite.</item>
               <item>The fift Leper, is the proud man.</item>
               <item>The ſixt Leper, is the Glutton.</item>
               <item>The ſeuenth Leper, is the Adulterer or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator.</item>
               <item>The eight Leper, is the Couetous man.</item>
               <item>The ninth Leper, is the Murtherer.</item>
               <item>The tenth Leper, is the Murmurer.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:4"/>
            <head>The firſt Leper, is the <hi>Schiſmatique.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Lephantiaſis, or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, is a diſeaſe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and full of poyſon, proceeding of Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and corrupt blood, inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the inwarde and outward parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole bodie, making it foule and filthie, inſomuch that the breath of the Leper is very contagious and infectious: for the which cauſe it hath euer inforced a ſeparation of ſuch from all companie: Euen ſo the Leproſie of ſinne, wherein we are borne and conceyued, cleaueth ſo faſt to our bones, and is ſo fixed in our heart, infecting all our powers and ſpirits, that our vnderſtanding cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend thoſe things which belong to the ſpirit of God, our wil abhorreth diuine and heauenly things, and finally the whole man is ſet on fire with vncleane deſires, and moſt filthie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations. And this contagion is ſo vehement throughout the whole life of man, and doth in ſuch wiſe ſhew foorth it ſelfe in all actions (though they ſeeme to be honeſt) that as they offend the maieſtie of God, ſo they giue occaſion of ſinning to others, and one infecteth another by their euill example: in ſo much as were it not for the vnſpeakable mercie and great goodneſſe of God (which is our ſupport and ſtay) we muſt needs be excluded from his preſence and Church, and ſo periſh for euer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:5"/>
            <p> And becauſe a Leproſie is not as euerie light diſeaſe, but a fearefull lothſome, contagious and ſeparatiue maladie (as is ſaid) it may aptly at this time repreſent, not onely all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners generally, but alſo certaine capitall and notorious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom I haue tearmed <hi>Engliſh Lepers,</hi> for that they haue infected many thouſands in this Chriſtian Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of England, and will in time (if the greater care be not had of the daunger that may enſue) vtterly deſtroy the whole bodie of the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, as one of the moſt noyſome, I haue ſet the Schiſmatique and ſedicious, whoſe malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent humor, firſt of all brought the corporall leproſie vppon the Iewes, as is to be ſeene, <hi>Num.</hi> 12. Now becauſe al actions are commonly knowne by their obiects, that is to ſay by the matter wherein they are imploied (as the ſight is knowne becauſe it apprehendeth the light, and diſcerneth colours, and the hearing likewiſe, in that it admitteth ſoundes and voyces) let vs ſee what the effect of Schiſme and ſedition is. It may truly be ſaid to effect and bring in priuation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of two moſt excellent things, that is to ſay, of Order, and of Vnitie.</p>
            <p>Order (according to Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> opinion) is that by which, all things, and all perſons, high or lowe, equall or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall, are diſpoſed and ſet in their proper places. All things in the world are not equall, and of like valour: but then they ſeeme to be ordered, when they are well diſpoſed and ſet in conuenient places: and humane actions haue then an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when things are framed according to their condition and worthines. Vpon the which matter <hi>Chriſostome</hi> hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably written in his Homilye 23. vpon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his Epiſtle to the Romanes, where hee ſaith, that becauſe equalitie of honour and condition, cauſeth oftentimes many diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, God hath ordained principalities, and many ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as that of the man and his wife: of the father and the ſonne: of the olde man and the yong: of the bond and the free: of the maſter and the ſeruant: of the teacher and the
<pb facs="tcp:19414:5"/>diſciple: and of the king and the ſubiect. And no maruaile if God hath appointed this order among men, when as he hath made the like in our bodies, as the head in the higheſt part, and therin the eyes as windowes: vnder them he hath placed the mouth to take in ſuſtenance and prouiſion for ſtrength: then the breaſt, to containe the vital parts: the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to concoct the meates: then the loynes, legges, and feete for ſupporters of the whole. The which being thus ordered within our view, do ſhew forth the great wiſedome of the workemaiſter. But if the ſaide parts be confounded, tranſpoſed, and out of order, they make not a man, but a monſter. The like is to be ſeene among beaſts, as in Bees, in Cranes, in flocks of ſheepe, and among wilde beaſts. The Sea is not without this diſcipline, where alſo innumerable ſculles of fiſhes, are defended and garded, vnder one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall leader. If God, in the creation of all liuing things, hath eſtabliſhed ſuch an order among the beaſts deuoide of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, how much more neceſſarie is it, that there be order for the good gouernment of men his moſt excellent creatures, to whom he hath made ſubiect all other things, that in God his moſt excellent common wealth there may be a ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie alſo and a ſubiection, a principalitie and an obedience among men according to their ſeuerall orders and degrees, without the which there can be no gouernment, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion? <hi>Anarchia,</hi> (or gouernment of ſtates, without a king) is of all regiments the worſt. For where there wanteth a chiefe heade, there the people are as ſheepe readie for the butcher. God gaue Iſrael in his wrath the choiſe of foure things, namely whether they would haue <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> a foole, to be their king: the Storke to rule ouer them: <hi>Aſſur,</hi> to be their king: or whether ſtill they woulde bee at this ſtay, <hi>Nullus Rex est nobis, quia non timuimus Iehouam.</hi> That is, We are deſtitute of a king, becauſe we haue not feared the Lord. To haue <hi>Rehoboam</hi> is ill: to haue <hi>Ieroboam</hi> is woorſe: to haue the king of <hi>Aſstria,</hi> is worſſe in the third degree: but <hi>Nullus Rex,</hi> No king, is woorſt of all. When there is no king, euerie man
<pb facs="tcp:19414:6"/>doth what liketh him beſt, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 17. Where there is no king men be like fiſhes, the great deuour the ſmall. Though it be ill to haue a Lion, or a Woolfe to be our king; yet it is better to haue one then many, to feare one then many. A prince is called the breath of our noſtrels, <hi>Iere.</hi> 20. And <hi>Daniel</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth him to a great ſhadowing tree. But if God ſend vs in ſteade of his good Angell an euill Angell: in ſteade of a tree to keepe vs from the heate of the Sunne, a Iuniper tree, which will ſuffer no plant to proſper neare it: in ſteade of light a ſtinking ſnuffe: it is I confeſſe a great curſſe: but if he take both the one and the other from vs, all his heauie diſpleaſure is fallen vpon vs. When <hi>Iacob</hi> had bleſſed his ſonnes with all good things, in the end, as if he had yeelded nothing without a ruler, he beſeecheth God to giue them a faithfull Ruler like <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> This order, and this gouernement therfore God hath giuen vnto his people from time to time, in his great loue and fauour for a bleſſing, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledgeth in the Pſalme, 77. Where he ſayth, <hi>Thou leddeſt thy people like ſheepe, by the handes of Moſes and Aaron.</hi> God him ſelfe is the General, and principall leader, (for the whole worlde is his) <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are but Gods hands, Gods lieutenants here in earth, the one with the worde, the other with the ſworde. They bee both Gods handes, Gods guides, and Gods paſtors. They both together may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the two Cherubims, with their wings ſpread to defend and couer the Arke. It is moſt true, that <hi>Natura non abundat in rebus ſuperfluis nec deficit in neceſſarys,</hi> Nature dooth not abound in ſuperfluous things, nor faile in neceſſarie things. It is a maimed bodie where either hand <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Aaron</hi> do want. The coniunction of both which, maketh a happie gouernment. For the which cauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> was glad of <hi>Aarons</hi> companie; <hi>He will be glad</hi> (ſaid God to <hi>Aron</hi>) <hi>when he ſeeth thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> So <hi>Dauid</hi> had his ſeeing <hi>Gad</hi> to be his watchman: he would not truſt his owne ſight onely. If <hi>Gad</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Dauids</hi> Seer, had ſeene no better then <hi>Dauid</hi> at one time, he and all his had beene loſt. The good that commeth by this
<pb facs="tcp:19414:6"/>coniunction, made king <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> not to vndertake his warres, vntil he had asked counſaile of the Prieſt. The which <hi>Ioſhua</hi> neglecting, made a couenant with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſhua <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> which he afterward too late repented. <hi>Aaron</hi> Gods high Prieſt, is, <hi>pro Rege, Lege, &amp; Grece.</hi> That is, He commaundeth the king to be honoured, the lawe to be kept, and the people to be loued. The people are of great power being a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, whom <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot gouerne well without <hi>Aarons</hi> hand. When <hi>Alexander</hi> came into <hi>India,</hi> and ſaw there the great <hi>Behemoth</hi> the Elephant, and <hi>Porus</hi> his little ſonne riding on his backe, and ruling him as he liſt, he wondred greatly and ſaid, <hi>Sivires ſuas noſcet, non reciperet ſeſſorem.</hi> If he knew his great ſtrength, he would not ſo eaſily be backed. So may it be ſaid of the multitude, that if they be not politiquely and wiſely gouerned, as well by the one as the other, they will not be eaſily commaunded. In ſimplicitie the people are like ſheepe, they liue by example. And the people haue this propertie of ſheepe, that if one leape into the ditch, all will follow that one. Therefore they muſt be led and gouerned by lenitie and faire meanes, not drawne by violence. If (ſaith <hi>Iacob</hi>) I ouerdriue the cattell, they will all die. <hi>Nimri</hi> was a ſore driuer: ſo was <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> but he loſt tenne parts of his flocke therefore. As the people are like ſheepe in ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo are they like the <hi>Chamelion</hi> in inconſtancie. They grudge that <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhould be high Prieſt,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>17.</hi> Num. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> though the Lorde make his rod to bud, for a manifeſt token that he is rightly called to that dignitie. And within a while after, he being dead, they mourne thirtie dayes for him. One while they ſay to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that whatſoeuer they commaunde they will do: but within a while after they are readie to ſtone them. One while they repent of their wickednes, in prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Lord: another while they chooſe new captaines to carrie them backe againe into Aegypt. Whereby we ſee that great care, policie and diſcretion, is neceſſarily required to be both in the Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall magiſtrate, for the ruling and gouerning of the multitude. As in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:7"/>ſo alſo in the newe, our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, and by the wiſedome of his ſpirite in his Apoſtles and their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors after his aſcenſion into heauen, made a difference of perſons, and eſtabliſhed an order for Ciuill, and alſo for Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall gouernment. Concerning ciuill magiſtracie, more ſhall be ſaide hereafter, vpon other occaſion. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Order, which Chriſt hath appointed among his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Prieſts, we know that firſt he choſe twelue, which afterward were called Apoſtles. After theſe he called ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie mo diſciples, which were not ſo famous as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt twelue. Beſide theſe, he ordained ſome to be Euangeliſts, and ſome Doctors, &amp;c. Afterward the Apoſtles elected certaine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men for the gouernment of the Church: as <hi>Timothie</hi> to be Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to be Archbiſhop of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iland <hi>Creta.</hi> In regard of which difference, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that ſome are worthie of double honor: therefore there were ſome which had but ſingle honor. Againe, the ſame Apoſtle ſayth, God hath not ſent me to baptiſe, but to preach: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth that ſome were to baptize, the which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle accounteth not ſo great an honour as preaching. This ſpirituall order and regement in all degrees, (as in Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Biſhops, Doctors, and Miniſters) was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as is alreadie ſhewed) by Chriſt, and ſhall be protected and propagated by the holy Ghoſt vnto the ende of the worlde. To theſe the Apoſtle ſpeaketh thus. <hi>Take heede to your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and to the whole flocke, wherein the holy Ghoſt hath placed you to rule the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloud.</hi> Alſo of theſe Biſhops and Eccleſiaſticall gouernours, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> ſpeaketh thus. <hi>Obey your Prelats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; be ſubiect to them, for they watch as being to giue an account of your ſoules.</hi> And that ancient father <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſayth, <hi>Opertet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationem ſequi traditionis quam tradiderunt patris ijs, quibus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittebant eccleſias. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Irenae. lib <hi>3.</hi> Chap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> We muſt follow the order of traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the fathers did leaue vnto them, vnto whom they did leaue the cure of Chriſtes people: vnto the which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the verie heathen comming vnto Chriſts flocke, did
<pb facs="tcp:19414:7"/>obey. Notwithſtanding theſe things, ſome raſhe heades be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Conchae,</hi> before they be <hi>Canales,</hi> that is to ſay, Spoutes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue filled their Ceſterne, and pretending a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in Religion, haue ſought to ouerthrow all good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Church-gouernment, bearing ignorant men in hand, that they haue ſufficient warrantize out of Gods worde. But as in the primatiue time of the Church, no hereſie was ſo bad, but that it would relie vpon one Scripture or other, as <hi>Arrius,</hi> who abuſed the 28. verſe, of the 14. Chapter of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpel for defence of his hereſie. <hi>Montanus</hi> the 16. verſe of the ſame Chapter for his hereſie. <hi>Manicheus</hi> the ſeuenth verſe of the ſecond Chapter to the <hi>Philippians</hi> for his hereſie. The late Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the 18. verſe of the 16. Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> for their error. The <hi>Familists</hi> the 21 verſe of the 17. Chapter of Saint <hi>Luke:</hi> Euen ſo, the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Schiſmatiques of this our age, haue choſen for their purpoſe the 25. verſe of the 22. Chapter of Saint <hi>Luke;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> the which they vſe as the Deuill vſed Scripture, who ſpake Gods worde, but not out of Gods mouth. And as the olde prophet in like caſe at <hi>Bethel,</hi> ſpake Gods worde, but not out of Gods mouth, therefore it helpeth them nothing at all.<note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 13.</note> And yet for all that ſo great is their enuie at other mens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, that ſo as they may bring downe the temple with this twine thread; they care not though it fall vppon their owne heades, as it did vpon <hi>Samſon.</hi> Whoſe enuie groweth hereof, becauſe by no means they can abide to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to obſerue order.</p>
            <p>As they do herein greatly offend, ſeeking through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to ouerthrow and confound all good order:<note place="margin">Vnitie.</note> ſo alſo by their bitter contention hereabout, they breake the Vnitie which ought to bee among brethren: then the which vnitie nothing ought to bee more deare to the Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Wherevpon Saint <hi>Luke</hi> in the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles commending the ſocietie of Chriſtians, ſayth: <hi>They were all of one mind, and of one heart.</hi> Alſo the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth vs in many places to obſerue order and vnitie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:19414:8"/>in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaying: <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lorde Ieſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>that ye all ſpeake one-thing, and that there be no Schiſmes or diſſentions among you: but be ye knit together in one minde, and in one iudgement.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee requireth among the faithfull a conſent in thought, worde, and deed, ſo neere as might be. As touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in action and deede, he ſpeaketh more plainely in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> where he ſayeth: <hi>Be ye like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accorde, and of one iudgement, that nothing be done through contention, or of vaineglorie.</hi> By which exhortation of the Apoſtle, wee may plainelie gather, that there are foure cauſes of ſedition at this day in the Church and common wealth. The firſt, a readineſſe to contende for euerie trifle: the ſecond, vaine-glorie: the thirde, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of preferment: the fourth, the diuerſitie of faith. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall contende, mooued by anie of theſe, hee will ſhewe himſelfe quickely a Schiſmatique, a falſe prophet, and a badde Paſtor. But it is no woonder to heare of falſe prophets, ſeeing there bee falſe Gods: no maruaile if there bee falſe Apoſtles, ſeeing there hath ſtart vp falſe Chriſtes. A man may boldlie ſay, the Diuell gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, when thoſe men came into the number of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Theſe men came not in deede, but as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, <hi>currebant,</hi> they ranne before they were ſent. And albeit they runne, yet when they come to the ſheepe-folde, they play as the Woolfe dooth, who commeth ſimplie and humblie, with his taile clapt cloſe betweene his legges, howling like a dogge, and comming ſoftlie agaynſt the winde, leaſt the ſheepe might ſmell him. They behaue themſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo like the enuious man that ſowed tares, who commeth when men ſlept: in the night, leaſt ſeene: ſoftlie, leaſt heard: into corners, leaſt found: with a maske, leaſt knowne: <hi>Clam dicens,</hi> preaching in parlours; an ancient marke of a falſe prophet.</p>
            <p>Theſe followers at the firſt are verie popular, they haue goodlie bleſſings, and manie faire woordes in their
<pb facs="tcp:19414:8"/>mouthes: their lippes are verie fayre and cleane burni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: and as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Habent hypocritae decoratiſsimas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes:</hi> Hypocrites can ſpeake pleaſant things: they will not for any thing ſpeake that which may diſpleaſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Phariſeis dare not acknowledge <hi>Iohn</hi> to bee a Prophete for offending the people: who alwayes haue this in requeſt, <hi>Loquere nobis placentia, &amp; frange nobu iuga.</hi> Speake vnto vs pleaſant things, and ſhake off the yoke from our neckes. Hee muſt winke at their vices: hee muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a publique faſt; vſe long prayer; and haue a verie narrowe ſtrayner for Gnattes. And thus vnder a ſheepes skinne, they conueigh into the ſheepefolde a Woolfe moſte rauenous. For poyſon is not mingled with Woormewood, but with ſweete wine, and put into a cuppe of golde.</p>
            <p>The Diuill came diſguiſed to <hi>Adam;</hi> and like an olde man to <hi>Saule.</hi> Alas (ſay they to the ignorant people) your cauſe is good: (this was <hi>Abſaloms</hi> ſheepes skinne:) but there was none to doe iuſtice: herein they play the Woolues. This hypocriſie and diſſembling of ſome, hath cauſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie weakelings to miſſlike and loath the profeſſion of the Goſpell. But to ſuch Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Non debent oues odiſſe vestes ſuas, quaeas induunt lupi:</hi> the ſheepe muſt like their garments neuer the woorſe, though Wolues weare them. Let them rather growe to that perfection of knowledge, that they may bee able to ſeparate the wheate from the chaffe. <hi>Sit electio, ſit &amp; reiectio, ſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramque praecedat diſcretio.</hi> Let there be an election, and reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but before either let there go diſcretion. Albeit the Aſſe be in a Lions skinne, yet a man may take him by the cares, and ſay, <hi>At hae non ſunt aures Leonicae:</hi> theſe are no Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eares. Some one thing or other will euer bewray a falſe prophet.</p>
            <p>If we iudge of a ſheepe by the outskin only: If we chooſe our cloth by the liſt: or deeme a Phariſei to be good by his long fringe or his broade philacterie, we may ſo bee eaſily
<pb facs="tcp:19414:9"/>deceiued. For Chriſtianitie is <hi>Rei,</hi> and not <hi>Speciei,</hi> a matter of ſubſtance, and not of forme. The Oiſtrich hath very gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant feathers, yet he cannot flie. Therefore if ye will trie and diſcerne betwene a falſe and a true prophet, ye ſhall do it by theſe two meanes, wherewith <hi>Iſaac</hi> tried his two ſonnes <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> And how is that? By voice, and hands. By the voice, in theſe three fruits yee ſhall know a falſe prophet. What prophets co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion ſoeuer hath either no fruit in it; or noiſome fruit: or vncircumciſed fruit, he is no true prophet. To heare, to pray, and to imbrace we knowe not what, is a Religion without fruite, a verball religion, ſuch as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes imbrace, who worſhip God in an vnknowne tongue. Whoſo deliuereth ſuch is a falſe prophet. Secondly if it be noiſome fruit, it is as the fruite of thornes and of briers, it is euer pricking, ſcratching, and tendeth to renting the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and common peace of brethren, maketh men to forſake mutuall loue and friendly ſocietie: and with <hi>Manaſses</hi> to build vp a temple in <hi>Gerezim</hi> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of Hieruſalem, which is great impietie. For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Ducentis error, duplex eſterror,</hi> The errour of the guide or leader, is a double errour, though he haue but two followers: but if he haue a hundred followers, then (ſayth he) it is <hi>centuplex,</hi> an hundred fold: If one thouſand, then it is <hi>milleplex,</hi> a thouſand fold Of ſuch leaders, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh alſo thus, <hi>Petro manen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti dixit Chriſtus, paſce oues meas:</hi> but, <hi>Schiſmatico vel heretice exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unti dicit Deus, Paſce haedos tuos:</hi> that is, To perſeuering <hi>Peter</hi> Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Feede my ſheepe:</hi> but to the Schiſmatique or Heretike which goeth out, God ſayth, <hi>Feede thy goates.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if it be vncircumciſed fruit, ſuch as giueth the glorie of God to the creature: to our election, <hi>Operapraeuiſae,</hi> Workes foreſeene of God: to our vocation, free will: and to our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, merite, and ſo by circumſtance doe make the death of Chriſt of none effect, they that deliuer it bee falſe prophets. As the voice is thus to bee diſcerned, ſo are the hands alſo to be felt, for they are not emptie, but are reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with fruit. For our confeſſion and prophecying is not
<pb facs="tcp:19414:9"/>all that is looked for at our hands. For to them that ſaid, <hi>Haue we not propheſied in thy name, &amp;c.</hi> It is anſwered by Chriſt, <hi>I knowe ye not.</hi> The eſpeciall fruits of the ſpirit that ſhould be in vs, are ſinceritie of the hart, humilitie of the mind, and loue to the brethren. Humilitie is not the fruit of the thorne or brier: but Sciſmatiques are proud and ſelfe-conceyted. There is nothing but they miſlike which themſelues do not. They are like vnto rhoſe <hi>Monkes</hi> which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> found fault withall <hi>Qui nuſquam putant lucere ſolem neci in cella ſua:</hi> which thinke that the ſunne ſhineth no where but in their cel. They thinke them ſelues ſo godly, wiſe, ſincere, pure, perfect and ſo Chriſtian that none is comparable to them: as if they alone, had an impropriation of Gods ſpirit. The male-content humor of the Ephraits troubleth them, and diſdainingly cauſeth them to demaunde, <hi>Why called ye vs not with you? Hinc ille lachrime.</hi> Herehence come the braule. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence it commeth that the ſheepheards of <hi>Gerar,</hi> and the ſheepheards of <hi>Iſaac</hi> cannot agree. Now not an Aegyptian and an Iſraelite, but two Iſraelites may bee ſeene, not to fight onely, but as it were to kill one another. Theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellers, are much incouraged by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine theſe braules, inſomuch that it cannot be ſaid of them, <hi>Vt Sacerdos, ſic populus,</hi> but the contrarie: <hi>Vtpopulus, ſic ſacerdos,</hi> As the people is, ſo is the Prieſt. Whereas, neither the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuches flatterie, <hi>Sit quaeſo ſermo tuns.</hi> Let thy ſpeach, I pray thee, bee like the reſt of the prophets: nor yet the peoples ſtones, ſhould ouer-rule the Miniſters of Chriſt, but ſhould rather hearken and follow Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> rule, <hi>Gaudeo quia facitis, ſed non faceo, quia facitis.</hi> I am glad that ye do well, but I do not well, becauſe ye doe ſo: for then if ye do ill, I muſt do ſo to: but I do well (ſaith he) becauſe it is good for me to do ſo. It is a thing moſt prepoſterous, and out of courſe for the ſheepe to gouerne and direct the ſheepheard; for the ſcholer to teach his maiſter; the yong ſtudent to ſet the graue doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to ſchoole, and to reproue the ancients of errour and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. But ſuch is our time now, wherein men are rather
<pb facs="tcp:19414:10"/>talkers then doers of Gods worde: and hauing tickeling tongues and wits, itching eares, and delighting in curious and contentious diſputes, they are not content to be taught plain &amp; ſimple faith, but ſeeke euery day after new teachers, and new things. And this commeth through their leuity and inconſtancie. At the firſt when Manna is ſtrange, they like it wonderfully, but ſoone after, <hi>Nauſeat anima noſtra,</hi> they loath it. They vſe a months diligence, or at the moſt they haue but ſix months liking. They wil ſoone find one cauill or other to miſlike, and will take exceptions againſt the beſt. <hi>Iſay</hi> is too long, and <hi>Obudia</hi> too ſhort, <hi>Peter</hi> keepeth company with them of the circumciſion, Chriſt with publicans and ſinners. Thus they like none, nor wil long be content with any. To this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie they ioyne alſo ſuch preſumption, as that with <hi>Peter</hi> they woulde bee makers of tabernacles, wherein they haue no skill, being not therunto called. Euery Cobler and baſe artificer will be buſie with Church-gouernment, not fearing this threatning,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſtranger that commeth nere the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ſhalbe ſlaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>19. 1.</hi> Sam. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> And againe, <hi>Whoſoeuer toucheth the mount ſhall ſurely die.</hi> See what vengeance befell the men of <hi>Bethſhames,</hi> becauſe they preſumed to looke into the Arke of the Lord. Beware of preſumption, and follow the counſaile of the wiſe man, ſaying: <hi>Search not out the things raſhly that are too hard for thee. Peters</hi> pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for being in hand with the building of the Tabernacles was, <hi>He wist not what he ſaid.</hi> And his fault is the leſſe, in that he leaueth it to be determined by Chriſt: but theſe rude and barbarous ſort, will not with any reaſon be anſwered, of whome this ſentence of Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified: <hi>Facilius eos vinci poſſe quam perſuaderi.</hi> They may more eaſily be ouercome then perſwaded. <hi>Cum diſputare neſciant, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigare tamen non deſinunt.</hi> Although they know not to diſpute, yet they leaue not of to wrangle. They are like vnto <hi>Samſons.</hi> Foxes, knit all together in the tailes, that is to ſay, vnited in euill, but in the head, that is in vertue and godlines, diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerered and diuided. As <hi>Samſon</hi> by his foxes deſtroied the corne of his enimies: ſo the diuell by his foxes, doth wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:19414:10"/>hinder the Lords harueſt. God open their eies (if it bee his will) that at the laſt they may ſee their wickedneſſe, that liuing in vnitie, they may yeelde obedience to their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and reuerently behaue themſelues towards the Lords Miniſters, a matter of great importance. Then would they ſay to the Lords <hi>Iehoſhua, Al that thou hast commanded vs we wil do, and whither thou ſendeſt vs we will go.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> A Romane ſouldier ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enemy down, &amp; ready to thruſt him through, the retreat then ſounding, ſpared him, and came ſpeedily to his fellowes. Being asked why he did let the enemie eſcape, he anſwered, I had rather obey, then conquer an enemie. O that al were of this mind, to yeeld obedience to magiſtrates, eſpecially to Chriſtian magiſtrates, ſuch as God hath at this day ſet ouer vs. If there be any thing out of frame in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church that offendeth you, withdrawe not your obedience, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. There was neuer any church here in earth ſo pure, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome blemiſh could not be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: neither hath there bene any religion or ſeruice of god ſo perfect, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hath bin free from al imperfections. That paſouer which was the beſt of al other, which hath this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 23.22.</note> 
               <hi>There was not the like ſince the daies of Samuel,</hi> had 4. notable imperfections in it.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 35.</note> Let vs know, that in religion there is both a centre &amp; a ſpace. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be beſt to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> centre, yet if we be not out of the ſpace we be well. Out of the ſpace is too bad, like as it is to be out of the But. What madnes is it then in thoſe men, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot be in the prick, wil not be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> but neither. This was at one time <hi>Peters</hi> extremity, <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou ſhals neuer waſh my feet:</hi> and incontinent he deſireth Chriſt to waſh both feet, head, hands, &amp; al. We muſt learn to keepe a mean,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and ſomtime to tollerate imperfections. <hi>Abram</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of ſpoiles, permitted that to <hi>Eſchol,</hi> and to <hi>Mamre,</hi> which hee would not do himſelfe. So <hi>Iob</hi> tollerated the feaſting of his ſonnes. So did <hi>Paul</hi> in the matter of receiuing ſtipend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that to others, which himſelf would not do. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay with a graue father, <hi>Si quid ſecus ſit,</hi> If things be not as they ſhoulde bee, <hi>Corrigi cupis.</hi> I deſire that they may
<pb facs="tcp:19414:11"/>be amended: if not amended, I deſire they may be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: if they be not taken away, <hi>tollero &amp; gemo,</hi> I ſuffer, and ſigh. Contention in this caſe helpeth not, but rather hurteth, and offendeth both God and good men. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> giueth this caueat,<note place="margin">Galat. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If ye bite and deuoure one another, take heede ye be not deuoured one of another.</hi> Vpon the which Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſayth, that contention is like vnto a moath, which neuer lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a peece of cloth vntill he hath conſumed it. Not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe therefore the Apoſtle wiſheth that they might be cut off which trouble the Church. Therefore, my brethren, be warned in time, though the magiſtrate vſeth not ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie, as this fault of yours deſerueth, yet knowe that God will not leaue you vnpuniſhed: who the more he ſuffereth, the greater will the vengeance be when he ſtriketh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſecond Leper, is the <hi>Church-robber.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Acriledge,</hi> is a purloining and incroching, either by violence or by ſubtletie to priuate vſe, holie things which are dedicated vnto God, or which are due vnto him, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a vow, or of a ſeparation. This definition of Sacriledge, plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that temporall goods and lands may be ſeparated from lay fee (ſo termed) to the maintenance of Biſhops, preachers, and miniſters of Gods holy word and ſacraments, that theſe may both be able to liue with neceſſarie maintenance, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeuerall orders and degrees, and alſo may haue ſufficient to keepe hoſpitalitie, and to relieue the poore, according to Gods will, to whome in reſpect hereof ſuch goods are here ſaid to be dedicated, and to be due as his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And further it may appeare, that all they which ſhall couerouſly vſurpe ſuch lands, goods or tithes ſo ſeparated,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:11"/>and imploy them to their owne priuate vſes, and ſpend them prodigally and vainly vpon their pleaſures, ſhall rob God of his right, and ſo be guiltie of that damnable ſinne of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge. It is therefore a matter more daungerous then worldlings make account of, to meddle with ſeparated and conſecrated things, which belong to him and his Prieſts. For this was the cauſe that <hi>Vzziah</hi> was ſtricken with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If God hath allowed, required, and bleſſed ſuch gifts, and the giuers, (as in his worde plainely appeareth that hee hath,) then muſt it needs follow, that it is lawfull for his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Miniſters to poſſeſſe ſuch goodes and liuings, as haue beene giuen of deuotion to the Church: and not to be like the begging Friers. That it is lawfull for Prelates and Miniſters of Gods worde to poſſeſſe temporall goods and lands giuen to maintenance of diuine ſeruice, the Scriptures doe plainly proue. In the olde teſtament God commaunded the children of Iſrael to giue vnto the Leuites,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of their poſſeſſion, Cities to dwell in, and the ſuburbs of the citie round about them, for their beaſts and cattell. Of the which cities, there were in all appointed fortie and eight. And theſe fields of the Leuites, were by expreſſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement forbidden by God to be alienated, that they might remaine vnto them for a perpetuall poſſeſſion, as appeareth in theſe words:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi> 25.34 <hi>Leui.</hi> 27.28.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing ſeparate from common vſe, that a man doth ſeparate vnto the Lord of all that he hath (whether it be man or beaſt, or land of his inheritance) may be ſolde nor redeemed. For euerie thing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from common vſe is moſt holy vnto the lorde.</hi> And this is not repugnant with that which is written in the 18. Chapter of the booke of <hi>Numbers,</hi> where the Prieſts and Leuits are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to haue anie part of inheritance with the other tribes, but their portion in tithes and oblations onely. For although in that firſt diuiſion of the lande of Iſrael, the Prieſts of that time, had no poſſeſſion of fieldes, yet afterwarde they had lands and poſſeſſions, by the vowes of the faithfull for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall inheritance. Therefore in the laſt Chapter of <hi>Leuit.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19414:12"/>where mention is made of lands and fields dedicated to the Lord, it is ſaid, that ſuch lands and fields ſo vowed and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, ſhalbe holy vnto the Lord, &amp; ſeparate from common vſe, the poſſeſſion whereof ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prieſts for euer. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in that ſecond partition of land in <hi>Iuda</hi> (wherof mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made in <hi>Ezechiels</hi> laſt chapter) which ſhould be after the captiuity, there was one great part aſſigned to the prieſts, an other leſſer part to the Leuites: and another to the princes: Moreouer,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> who was of the tribe of <hi>Leuy,</hi> and the ſon of <hi>Hilkaih,</hi> one of the Prieſts of <hi>Anathoth,</hi> bought a field of <hi>Hanameel</hi> his vncles ſon,<note place="margin">Iere. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> becauſe the title by kinred appertained vnto him to buy it. By theſe teſtimonies it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, that it was lawful for the Prieſts &amp; Leuits not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the negatiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement in the booke of <hi>Numb.</hi> to purchaſe &amp; poſſeſſe fields &amp; lands,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> dedicated to the lord.</p>
            <p>In the new teſtament alſo, it is ſaid in a common prouerb, <hi>The labourer is worthie of his reward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Which prouerbe being true, Chriſt and his Appoſtles made vſe of the ſame. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſayeth, that they which ſowe ſpirituall things, ſhould reape temporall things. The which exchaunge is like vnto that of <hi>Diomedes</hi> and <hi>Glaucus,</hi> who for his golden armor, tooke of <hi>Diomedes</hi> a brazen harneſſe.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> Of this matter the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh at large in the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> where he demaundeth this queſtion: <hi>Who goeth a warrefare at his owne charges?</hi> Further, he alledgeth out of the law, <hi>Thou ſhalt not mooſell the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi> Then, if meate muſt be plentifully giuen vnto the cattell which labour for our liuing, why ſhall not things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the maintenance of Paſtors and teachers, which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour day and night for the ſaluation of ſoules, be giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them? Sheepheards haue fruit and liuing of their flocke. Are not husbandmen and planters of vines maintained by their labours and fruits? Euen ſo the Miniſters of Chriſt, when they feede the children of God, and husband them as the ſpirituall husbandrie haue a right to bee nouriſhed and ſuſtained thereby. <hi>Chriſostome</hi> to the people of his time,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:12"/>which vſed to ſay, that the biſhops &amp; miniſters liued on their coſts, anſwereth thus: <hi>No,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the time of the law we liued on the Altar. Before they gaue it, it was theirs, but after it was Gods, and he gaue it to his priests: So in the Goſpell</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to giue vs men, but to God,</hi> Reddite Deo quae ſunt Dei: <hi>Giue vnto God the things that are Gods: and he againe giueth it vnto vs his Ministers.</hi> And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to this effect hath a notable ſaying, <hi>O homo meus est &amp; mea ſunt omnia quae habes, &amp;c.</hi> O man, thy ſelfe art mine, &amp; all that thou poſſeſſeſt. The earth which thou tilleſt is mine: the ſeed which thou ſoweſt is mine: the cattel which thou wearieſt with labor are mine: the Sunne is mine: and the ſhowers of the early and latter raine are mine: <hi>Tu quia manum admonisti, &amp;c.</hi> Thou, becauſe thou haſt lent me thy hand to holde the plough, take thou one part for thy labour. If God (ſaieth he) ſhould ſay thus vnto vs, it were more then he ought vs, or then we could require. But take thee nine partes (ſayth he) O man, onely giue me the tenth. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſayth, that the Elders are worthie of double honour,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> eſpecially they that labour in the word and doctrine. For thoſe fathers and ancients which haue worne and ſpent themſelues, ſo that they cannot labor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word as afore time, by reaſon of age &amp; diſeaſes, ought to be excuſed, and yet neuertheleſſe cheriſhed and honoured, as if they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored. For as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith. <hi>Nihil eſt in hac vita difficili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, laborioſus, &amp; periculoſius epiſcopi, aut presbiteri officio.</hi> There is nothing in this life more hard, more painfull, and more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous, then the office of a Biſhop or prieſt. But for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to vndergo the great burthen thereof, it hath pleaſed God to giue vnto them in this world, more then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon honor, that is to ſay, double honor. Alſo S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Honores &amp; dignitates eccleſiaſticas non ignoro deberi his, qui eas digne ſecundum Deum, administrare &amp; velint, &amp; poſsint.</hi> I am not ignorant that Eccleſiaſticall honours and dignities are due vnto them, which both can and will vſe them well and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For according to the Prouerb, <hi>Honos alit artes:</hi> Honor che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth lerning. Theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, it may appeare how
<pb facs="tcp:19414:13"/>greatly they ſinne againſt God, which in theſe dayes ſeeke all they can to diſhonour them, whom God and his worde doth honour: As do not onely the Anabaptiſts, but alſo manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which would be counted zealous profeſſors of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and yet defend and maintaine ſuch as write, preach, and ſpeake againſt godly Biſhops and Prelats. The ſinne of ſuch vndoubtedly, is no leſſe then Sacriledge, in that they robbe God of his honour. For as they that honour Gods Miniſters, honour God: ſo they that ſeeke to take from them their due honour, do diſhonour God. In the Arke of olde time there were three famous things, Manna, <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, and the two Tables. Our Arke had theſe ſomtime, but ſome greedy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants haue pried into our Arke, haue taken away a great part of our Manna, and to get the remainder, they ſnatch at <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, that is at Church-gouernment and diſcipline, and by their good willes, would leaue nothing but the two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that is, ſcholers bookes to liue by. But if <hi>Samuel</hi> be not <hi>vir honoratus,</hi> a man of honour among the people, neuer looke for a good gouernment. If the crib be emptie, ye ſhal get no Oxen: ye muſt be content to haue Aſſes to do your worke. If the carkas be gone, ye may perhaps with a little chaffe get Buſſards,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.</note> but Eagles wil not come. If <hi>Siſac</hi> ſpoile the temple, then <hi>Salomons</hi> golden ſhields, ſhall be turned into <hi>Rehoboams</hi> brazen ſhields, and yet ye muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with it, &amp; with much more euill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe, which the pretended reformation will bring vpon you, and your poſteritie. Whatſoeuer refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is pretented, the golde of the Temple is intended. They are of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> religion, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the temple, and ſeeing <hi>Iupiters</hi> coate to be rich of beaten golde and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, tooke it away, ſaying, that it was too colde for winter, and too heauie and hote for ſommer: and in ſteade thereof, gaue him a coate of Linſey-woolſey. And beholding alſo <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Apollo,</hi> with a golden beard, hee tooke it from him, ſaying, It was a ſhame the ſonne ſhoulde haue a beard, ſith the father had none. Thus we ſee that theſe kinde of men will alwaies haue a cloke to couer their inſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:19414:13"/>couetouſnes. With theſe men, whatſoeuer is beſtowed vppon learning and deuinitie, is <hi>(Vt quid predicio haec)</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and loſt. There is ſome controuerſie among doctors whether <hi>Diocleſians, or Iulianus</hi> perſecution were the greater. <hi>Iulianus occidit presbiterium, Iulian</hi> killed the preiſthood, he rife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their liuings, imbeſeled the patrimonie of the Church. But <hi>Diocleſian occidit presbetoros,</hi> killed the preiſtes and cut of theyr heades. And the ſayde Doctors conclude, that <hi>Iulianus</hi> was far woorſe, for (ſay they) by <hi>Diocleſians</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion men died, but the church floriſhed: and by <hi>Iulianus</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution <hi>nomen ipſum Chriſtianiſmi pene perijt,</hi> there was ſcarſe any remembrance of chriſtianſme left. In like caſe it is to be feared that the hazard of Religion which may come by this ſecret inuaſion will be greater then that which ſhall be by open perſecution. Becauſe liuing and mainteinance, (which is the reward of learning) being taken awaie, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſme muſt needs enſue, and ſo at the laſt no Religion. <hi>Saul</hi> is well content his men ſhould doe good ſeruice in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the enimie, but hee grudgeth them to eate of the honie, that ſhoulde cleare their eies, and comforte their hart. But as church-maintenance is of ſome grudged, and of other ſome couetouſly &amp; iniuſtly ſought, ſo the ſame ought not to be alienated from the right vſe, but ought to be kept, &amp; as vnwillingly yelded, as was <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard. For Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> would not deliuer the ſubſtance of the church vnto <hi>Valence</hi> the Emperour, when he required the ſame, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed it on the poore. I deny not, but that kings &amp; Princes are to command all both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies and goods of all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects within their dominions, to ſerue their turnes in time of need. Yet, with out great and extreame neceſſitie in deede, thereunto enforcing, the goods and lyuings of the Church ought to be kept and preſerued, and are not raſhly to be imployed. It is reported of a certaine noble man, who liued at <hi>Carthage,</hi> that franckly and of his owne accorde, hee gaue to the Church of <hi>Hippo</hi> (whereof Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had the charge) a poſſeſſion by writings vnder ſeale: which
<pb facs="tcp:19414:14"/>writings he deliuered to Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> and to his Cleargy men, reſeruing onely vnto himſelfe the profite of the lande during his life: but afterward repenting him of his liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and former graunt, he required his land againe, offering in lue thereof, fiue poundes to bee giuen vnto the poore. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſeeing this, lamented and ſorrowed, not for the poſſeſſions demaunded againe, but for the inconſtancie of men: and being a man of a verie gentle and milde nature, yeelded it backe againe, which hee might haue kept in the right of the Church. And hereof groweth a queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Augustine</hi> could of himſelfe, without a general conſent of the Church, alienate that land, wherewith that ſame was once rightly endewed. But whether <hi>Auguſtin</hi> offended here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or no, I will leaue that to others to be decided: this I am ſure cannot be denied, but that the inconſtancie of the giuer deſerued blame. Yet this man had more reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to require that again which he once gaue, then thoſe church-robbers haue at this day, who with <hi>Athalia</hi> think they neuer haue inough, till they ruſh into the Lords treaſurie, and rob his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, notwithſtanding that neither their ancetors brought ſo much as one bricke to the foundation, nor themſelues a tile to couer the roofe therof. If the law of God confirme the law of natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by which euery man inioyeth his right, why ſhould not the law of nations confirme the law of God. God in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie</hi> calleth the detaining of his tythes, a ſpoyling of him. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel he calleth it a deceyuing of the holy Ghoſt to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife. What vengeance therof enſued the ſtorie ſheweth. Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Si in ignem mittitur, qui non dedit rem propriam, vbi putas mittendus est qui in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſit alienam?</hi> If he be caſt into the fire, which hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of his owne ſubſtance, what thinkeſt thou ſhall become of him, who hath taken the ſpoyle of that which belonged to others? Beſide the daunger of damnation (whereof Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) he &amp; his poſteritie, may daily expect and feare that vengeance, which befell an Eagle, which vpon a time being hungrie, and ſeeking for her pray, hapned to flie
<pb facs="tcp:19414:14"/>ouer an altar wherupon there was fleſh to be ſacrificed to an idol god. With this fleſh the Eagle gorged her ſelfe, &amp; tooke of it alſo to carie to her neſt to feed her yong ones. With the ſame ſhe fortuned to carrie a cole of fire vnawares, which cleaued thereunto, wherewithall both her ſelfe, her neſt, and her yong, were vtterly burnt and deſtroyed. The like may befall thoſe Cormorants, which hauing <hi>Caninum appetitum,</hi> a Doglike appetite, eating till they vomit, through an inſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſire of ſpoile, neither foreſeeing the danger, nor fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what may inſue, ceaze vpon all whatſoeuer commeth within their reach: wherewithall they carie the heauie ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, which wil not onely fire them &amp; their neſts, which through rapine, oppreſſion, and deceit, they haue buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on hie in this world, but alſo without great repentance caſteth them downe headlong into hell fire which burneth for euer. For God will not ſuffer <hi>Sacriledge</hi> to eſcape vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. When <hi>Balthazar</hi> with his Queene and Lords, dranke in the ſiluer and golden veſſels, which his father <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> had taken out of the temple of Hieruſalem. In the ſame verie houre there appeared fingers, as if they had beene of a mans hand, writing right ouer the candleſticke vpon the plaine wall in the kings palace: and the king ſaw the palme of the hand that wrote, the effect of that which was ſo written was, <hi>God hath numbred this kingdome, and brought it to an ende: thou art weighed in a ballance, and art found too light: thy kingdome is dealt in parts, and giuen to the Medes and Perſes.</hi> The verie ſelfe ſame night was <hi>Balthazar</hi> the king of the <hi>Chaldes</hi> ſlaine, and <hi>Darius</hi> ſucceded in the kingdom of the <hi>Medes.</hi> Whereby it plainly appeareth, that as thoſe things which are dedicated to the Church, doe belong vnto God, ſo the ſpoylers and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſpenders of his portion, can haue no ſecuritie, but a fearefull expectation of vengeance from heauen. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as contrariwiſe they that doe giue liberallie to the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and maintenance of the woorſhippe and ſeruice of almightie God, and which (if they haue not to giue) do yet at the leaſt in heart, wiſh well vnto the ſame, doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb facs="tcp:19414:15"/>vnto themſelues &amp; to their poſterity a ſingular bleſſing and fauour from God.<note place="margin">Malac. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bring ye</hi> (ſaith the Lorde) <hi>all the tythes into the ſtore houſe, that there may be meate in my houſe; and proue me now herewithall ſaith the Lord of hoſtes, if I will not open the windows of heauen vnto you, and poure you out a bleſsing without meaſure. And I wil rebuke the deuourer for your ſake, and he ſhal not deſtroy the fruit of your ground, neither ſhall your vine be barren in the field, ſaith the Lorde of hoſtes, And all nations ſhall call you bleſſed: for ye ſhall be a pleaſant lande ſaith the lorde of hoſtes.</hi> A great bleſſing in deede, wherein the lord promiſeth not onely aboundance of fruit, but alſo to giue a bleſſed and holy name among all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he will vndoubtedly geue to al thoſe which will proue him herein, whether he will be iuſt a rewarder and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſer or no. Proue the Lord then for he is moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and iuſt in all his promiſes. He is not as a man that lieth, nor as the ſonnes of men that doth repent them after their promiſe and vowes. Hee ſpeaketh not the thing, but he doth it. Heauen and earth ſhall ſooner paſſe, then he will faile in a iot of his promiſes. If wordly minded men, could be perſwaded herein (as they would verie redilie in deed if they had faith) they would not offer vnto the Lord, the hault and the blinde, and the lameſt of the flockes: but would with <hi>Abel</hi> bring the beſt vnto him,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> who was therefore bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of God. Who afterward gaue the ſame in commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſaing,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ye ſhall ſeperate vnto the Lordes treaſurie, things that be chiefe, and moſt principall.</hi> The Lord loueth a cherefull and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall giuer, ſuch a one was king <hi>Dauid, who ſaid,</hi> I <hi>haue giuen all thinges with a glad heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>euen a good will, and now haue I had ioie to ſee thy people which here are preſent, offer with a free will vnto thee.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, ſo longe as he bent him ſelfe to the building of Gods houſe, ſo long he had peace. Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my brethren) the wrath of God on the one ſide, which will ſend ſpeedy vengeance, vppon all thoſe that commit <hi>Sacriledge:</hi> and his bleſſings on the other ſide promiſed to all thoſe which loue him and ſeeke the honour of his name moue you to beware of that damnable ſinne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:15"/>
            <head>The thirde Leper, is the <hi>Simoniac.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Jmony,</hi> is a ſelling of the gifts of the ſpirite, or of any ſuch thing, through a couetous deſire: the buier hauing an ambicious intent to prefer himſelfe thereby, and to make his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſerue his corrupt mind. Whereby it appeareth, that both the ſeller and the buier of ſpirituall things are <hi>Simoniacks,</hi> and infected with the leproſie of <hi>Geheſi,</hi> who tooke of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> for his cleanſing, that which his maiſter <hi>Elizeus</hi> refuſed.<note place="margin">4. <hi>King.</hi> 5.</note> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Simonie,</hi> the olde Schoole-men and Papiſts haue diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at large: who could beſt ſpeake herein, not onely by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, but alſo by practize. For whereas this is the onelie marke of all the olde and newe Teſtament, that the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhed vpon the tree of the Croſſe, is the ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſinnes of all thoſe that beleeue in him: the Pope and his hath a long time borne the world in hand, that he is the treaſurer of this great raunſome paid for our ſinnes, and that to be partaker thereof, men muſt come vnto him, and he will diſtribute this benefite to whom he thinketh good. And thereupon euery man began to buie ſaluation of him, which the onely blood of Ieſus Chriſt had purchaſed for vs, and which no other thing beſides could purchaſe. If thou haddeſt committed all the faults in the world, thou mighteſt haue had recourſe to the Popes pardons and indulgences. All of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, euen to murthers, inceſteſts, Sodomitries, were taxed and ſet at a certaine ſumme of money, and paying that the Pope would giue thee full remiſſion thereof. This pardon was ratified and deliuered to him that would giue moſt: and the booke of taxes doth confirme it, which was imprinted by their owne conſent, before the light of the Goſpel was made cleare againe in theſe laſt ages. Theſe Indulgences they ſold
<pb facs="tcp:19414:16"/>firſt to certaine perſons, and after to families, and then to townes, &amp; ſo in time to common wealthes, and whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, without exception of any perſons, yea for the terme of foure thouſand yeares of true pardon. The doctrine of Chriſt was: <hi>Hee that ſhall beleeue in mee ſhall haue remiſsion of ſinnes:</hi> That of the Popes: <hi>Hee that ſhall giue mee money, there ſhall be no hell for him.</hi> If you deſired Paradice, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Angels to carrie you thither, and all your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and friendes, as appeareth by the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the fift. For the knights of the order of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> If anie feared Purgatorie, hauing committed all the miſchiefes in the worlde, yea hauing lyne with the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine <hi>Marie,</hi> (as the preachers of the pardons in Germanie ſay) ſo ſoone as hee hath caſt ſiluer into the Baſon, their ſoules were by and by ſet at libertie therefrom. And to this ende they haue ſolde Trentals of Maſſes and Diriges, for ſoules departed. Whereby they haue ſet to ſale for money Chriſt himſelfe, valuing his moſt precious bodie at a lower price then euer <hi>Iudas</hi> did. This was <hi>Simonie</hi> in the higheſt degree moſte abhominable. Chriſt ſometime thruſt buiers and ſellers out of the Temple. But the Pope hath receyued in buiers and ſellers, and thruſt out Chriſt, and ſo haue turned the houſe of God into a denne of theeues. And thereof came this Prouerbe, <hi>Curia Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, non captat ouem ſine lana.</hi> The Court of Rome will not take the ſheepe without the fleece. Which alſo verefieth theſe words of <hi>Mantuan.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>venalia nobis:</l>
               <l>Templa ſecerdotes, altaria, ſacra, coronae,</l>
               <l>ignis, thura, preces, coelum est venale Deuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is, Amongſt vs in Rome, churches, prieſts, altars, maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, crownes, fire, incenſe, praier, and heauen are ſet to ſale, yea God himſelfe among vs may be had for money. Of this <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> our countri-man, made wofull complaint, at what time for his wilfull diſobedience and treaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt the king, he had fled for aid and ſuccor to Rome, and
<pb facs="tcp:19414:16"/>ſaw that nothing would be wrought there without money, and enforced with ſorrow for the ſame, he wrote thus to the Biſhop of <hi>Menze, Mater Roma facta est meretrix, &amp; proſtituta eſt pro mercede.</hi> Rome our mother is become a harlot, and for money and meed laieth herſelfe to ſale. The deteſtable <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> practiſed in the Church of Rome, in the daies of Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ninth, was the cauſe why the Greeke church vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brake from the Romans. I would to God, it might make a perfect ſeparation for euer betwene them and vs, vntill ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God to make them ſee their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſo repent them and conuert. In the meane time, beware of thoſe ſcorpions &amp; locuſts which are come out of the bottomleſſe ſmoking pit,<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> who although they haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faces of men, and wander vp and downe ſecretly in this realme in a diſguiſed maner like ruffians, with feathers, and all orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of light coloured apparel, like to the faſhion of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, or otherwiſe as they thinke beſt for their ſecuritie and ſafety: yet I ſay againe, take heed of them: becauſe they haue ſtings in their tailes. For though they haue a glorious name of pretended holines, calling themſelues <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> yet do they intiſe all maner of perſons with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dare aduenture to ſpeake, not onely to be reconciled to the Pope and church of Rome, but alſo to induce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by vowes &amp; othes to renounce their obedience to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Q. maieſtie, to denie her to be their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be diſcharged of their allegeance: &amp; to repute al magiſtrats vnder her, to be vnlawful, &amp; in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not to be obeied. And where they get footing &amp; entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there they deliuer their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated tokens &amp; relicks, as <hi>Agnus deis, grana benedicta, medellas, croſſes, beads,</hi> &amp; ſuch like traſh: &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further, bearing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people in hand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for mony by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſhal haue pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for al their ſins paſt. By which exchange, they draw vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues no ſmal adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. But of ſuch ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; fooliſh buiers, this may be verified. <hi>Quid dedit, auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuit, quod perdidit anima fuit.</hi> That which he gaue was gold: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he loſt was his ſoule. And to the bad marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which ſel ſuch deceitful traſh: it may as truly be ſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:17"/>
               <hi>Quod accepit aurum fuit; quod dedit, lepra fuit,</hi> That which hee tooke was golde; but that which hee gaue was a leproſie. Therfore in ſhunning of theſe men, or rather monſters, men ſhal not onely ſhunne a leproſie, but alſo deliuer themſelues from thoſe vglie and vncleane ſpirites (whereof Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh) which are come out of the mouth of the Dragon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 16.13</note> and out of the mouth of the beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe prophet. For they are the ſpirits of diuels, working myracles, to go vnto the kings of the earth, and of the whole worlde, to gather them to the battell. Such is their affected malice to attempt, and their infected means to obtaine their conqueſt, and our fall.</p>
            <p>There are alſo another ſort of Simonia call lepers, ſuch as be patrones of benefices, who hauing power to appoint a godly, learned, and diſcreete paſtor, to the congregation and Church, whereof they ought in deed to be patrons, that is to ſay, carefull and prouident fathers: yet neuertheles ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after their owne priuate gaine, rather then the gaining of mens ſoules, do (contrarie to the law of God and man) ſell their benefices and donations for money. And ſo refuſing to admit thoſe which be worthie, but preferring thoſe which be vnworthie, they call to the inheritance of Gods ſanctuarie, Schiſmatiques, ſeditious perſons, Atheiſts, ignorant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Aſſes, flatterers, and ſometime their owne kinſmen, and familiars, how vnmeete ſoeuer. They eſteeme the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a man, and receiue gifts. And thus, ſo much is in them, they make the houſe of God a houſe of marchandize, and a den of theeues. So that as he who being in Rome, did ſeeke for Rome: euen ſo may we among theſe kind of men, which ſuch patrons bring in, ſeeke long inough, and not find a good paſtor: but rather thoſe theeues, whereof our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> which come not in by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doore, but at the window. There haue beene the more of theſe pettie theeues, by the meanes of theſe great theeues. For our vſuall prouerbe is not ſo common as true, that if there were no receiuers, there would be no theeues. <hi>Socrates</hi> being asked on a time, why he
<pb facs="tcp:19414:17"/>laughed, anſwering he ſayde, I ſee great theeues lead ſmall theeues to the gallowes, which are more worthie to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelues then them: for (ſaith he) the ſmall robberies are puniſhed, but the great are caried in triumphes. Euen ſo thoſe great theeues, which rob the purſe of a poore miniſter, for that which ſhould freely be giuen vnto him: which rob the Church alſo of a learned and good paſtor for filthie lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, and which is woorſt of all, which rob God of his honor and ſeruice, by bringing into the ſheepefolde ſometimes a Woolfe and a theefe: thoſe are the theeues would bee more neerly looked vnto, then commonly they be. For as <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> ſayth, <hi>He that is not aſhamed to ſay, Quid mihi dabis, vt tibi iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam faciam,</hi> What wilt thou giue me to do thee iuſtice? Is it not all one as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Quid vis mihi dare, vt deum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> What wilt thou giue me to ſell God vnto thee? If theſe men do not waſh and cleanſe their hands in time from this leproſie by true repentance and amendment, it wil not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make a feareful ſeparation betwene God &amp; them, but wil alſo in this world bring at the laſt a conſumption of their whole ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For albeit (as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his paſtoral ſaith) that euill beginnings haue a prepoſterous end: as <hi>Iacob</hi> by ſupplantation attained to a bleſſing: the corne ſowed with a leprous hand, is reaped cleane: a faire child may be begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and borne betwene two adulterers: and the monie got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Simonie</hi> may haue a good iſſue, when it is beſtowed vpon the good of the poore: yet ſaith hee, this is no defence for <hi>Simoniacks.</hi> God will not be pleaſed with ſuch a ſacrifice as is gotten by robberie and deceite. As this concerneth the Patrone, ſo let the Miniſter take heede, that ſeeketh to come in at the window like a theefe, that he bee not defiled with this leproſie; But let them remember this ſentence of Saint <hi>Augustine, Diligendus est pastor: tollerandus eſt Mercenarius: cauendus eſt latro.</hi> A good ſheepheard is to be loued: a hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is to be tollerated: but a theefe of all other is to bee ſhunned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:18"/>
            <head>The fourth Leper, is the <hi>Hypocrite.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His mans Lerpoſie is a bad colour in the outskinne: of the which the Lord ſpeaketh thus to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The man that ſhall haue in the skin of his fleſh a ſwelling, or a ſcabbe, or a white ſpot, ſo that in the skinne of his fleſh it bee like the plague of leproſie, then hee ſhall bee brought to Aaronthe Priest, &amp;c.</hi> Hypocrites haue a diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of colour in the skinne, becauſe through a proude ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie they endeuour to differ from other men, both in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and in conuerſation. Neuertheleſſe, they haue another colour vnder the skinne in the fleſh, pretending one thing outwardly, and being otherwiſe within: hauing one thing in the mouth, and another thing in the heart: outwardly a falſe ſhew of godlines, and within full of all iniquitie. Such as were they of whome Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh thus, <hi>The Prieſts and Scribes watched him, and ſent forth ſpies, which ſhoulde feigne themſelues iust men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to take him in his talke, &amp;c.</hi> Of this Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing vpon the <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 63, ſaieth thus, <hi>Simulata ſanctitas, non eſt iniquitas, ſed duplex iniquitas: quia iniquitas eſt &amp; ſimulatio.</hi> Feigned holineſſe is not ſimplie iniquitie, but double iniquitie: becauſe it is both iniquitie, and diſſimulation. For this cauſe our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Except your righteouſneſſe exceede the righteouſneſse of the Scribes and Phariſeis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ye cannot enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſeis was vaine, and full of oſtentation, by which they ſought to be prayſed of men. They faſted, they prayed, they gaue almes, &amp;c. that they might be ſeene of men. Their righteouſneſſe was in worde, but not in deede, as Chriſt himſelfe teſtifieth of them. <hi>They ſay</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>and doe not. For they binde heauie burthens, and grieuous to be borne, and lay them on mens ſhoulders, but they
<pb facs="tcp:19414:18"/>themſelues will not mooue them with one of their fingers.</hi> To teach, and not to doe, condemneth the teacher. And therefore of Chriſt the true Doctor, it is ſayde, <hi>That hee began to doe and to teach.</hi> Of ſuch Doctours, which teach and doe not,<note place="margin">Acts. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> writeth thus. <hi>Vult hypocrita ſcire diuina eloquia, nec tamen facere: vult docte loqui, nec tamen viuere.</hi> The hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite deſireth to knowe the woorde of God, but not to practize it: to ſpeake learnedly, but not to liue thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And if it fortune that theſe doe anie thing that ſeemeth good, yet the intention of the ſame is not good, but rather they doe it to an hypocriticall ende. And therefore Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> of this phariſaicall righteouſneſſe ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Phariſeorum iuſtitia erat in ostentatione, &amp; non in rectitudine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionis, in locutione, non in opere: in corporis afflictione, non in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorum obſeruatione, &amp;c.</hi> The righteouſneſſe of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis was in the oſtentation of the worke, not in the vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſinceritie of the intention: in ſpeaking, not in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: in the affliction of the bodie, not in the keeping of the commandements: and in the leſſer obſeruations, leauing the more weighty things of the law. Theſe hypocrites which ſeeme to be religious worſhippers of God, and are not, are politike <hi>Machiuilians,</hi> which make a ſhew to loue the goſpel, but it is either to gaine credite therby, or to get gaine &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, or elſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe their ſubtil deuiſes. But deteſtable and diueliſh is their hypocriſie, who to attain to any digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, either eccleſiaſticall or ciuill: or elſe to make their falſe doctrine the more eaſily receyued and imbraced, doe feigne to haue that holineſſe, which they haue not, nor yet regard. Such hypocrites may fitly be compared vnto falling ſtarres which men call <hi>Aſſub,</hi> which in the night time, ſeeme to be in the Firmament, and to bee true ſtarres in deede, and yet are not ſo, but certaine fatte exhalations onely lifted vp from the earth, which being eleuated through the vpper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the ayre, are kindled by the heate and force of the vppermoſt Element, which is fire: and ſo being kindled, doe fall againe: euenſo theſe hypocrites, vnto men that
<pb facs="tcp:19414:19"/>looke not into them, ſeeme to be ſperituall light inflamed of God, and are thought in minde to be conuerſant in heauen, when as in trueth they are nothing leſſe.<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> As therefore the light of ſuch ſuppoſed ſtarres, is momentany and vaniſhing, euen ſo is the ioy of hypocrites. For what is the ioy &amp; hope of al hypocrites in their workes and actions? ſurely nothing but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuerence of honor, the glory of praiſe, to be feared of better men then them ſelues, &amp; of all men to be called holy. This is theyr ioie, and therefore theyr only portion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. They are like vnto image-caruers, who haue a care only to poliſh, paint and beautifie the outwarde forme to pleaſe the beholders, not caring for the backe partes, or for that which is in ward: and when they haue done all that they can, yet can giue no life vnto it. So the hypocrite ſeemeth to be holy in the ſight of men, and therfore behaueth him ſelfe accordingly, painting his actions with a ſhew of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whereas neuertheles within, both his inwarde partes, which are alwaies, in the ſight of God, and alſo his backe partes, that is to ſaie, the end of his life, and the iudgement of God are neglected. Therefore an hypocrite is but as a picture or ſhadow of a righteous man, and without truth and life. There is as great defference betwene the working of hypocriſie &amp; the working of grace, as betwene the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of arte, and the operation of nature. Art worketh only outwardly, as may appeare by the arte of grauing, caruing, and painting, &amp; ſuch like. But nature worketh firſt inwarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as is manifeſtly to be ſeene in the generation of liuing creatures, in whom the heart, and other vitall members, are firſt formed. For grace worketh firſt inwardly, &amp; reformeth the mind, through the loue of God &amp; the loue of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: Afterward it reformeth mens tongues, their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and their whole life: of the which the Apoſtle wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Be ye renued in the ſpirite of your mind, and put on the newe man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe.</hi> But agaynſt hypocriſie and diſſimulation which is in the outwarde man, Chriſt pronounceth this curſe;
<pb facs="tcp:19414:19"/>
               <hi>Wo vnto you Scribes and Phariſeis, yee are like vnto painted ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, which appeare beautifull outwarde, but within are full of dead mens bones, and all filthineſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wo vnto you Scribes and Phariſeis hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites: for ye make cleane the vtter ſide of the cuppe, and of the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but within ye are full of briberie and exceſſe.</hi> The righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſeis, was ſeuere and cruell: for they vrged the lawe of Retaliation, and required an eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth. This kinde hath fiue notes to know them to bee hypocrites by. 1 Firſt, their care is not on themſelues, but on others: and therefore enquire they after other mens actions, <hi>Quid autemiſte?</hi> What ſhall he here do? 2 They are euer <hi>Obſeruatores;</hi> narrow lookers vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens faults. 3 They are readie to controule and to condemne, whereas others more fitte, are not ſo forwarde. 4 They make choyſe of a brother that hath a moate in his eye: can they find none that hath a beame? They will not perchance meddle with them, for that they be of their owne kinde. Theſe Phariſeis let <hi>Herods</hi> and <hi>Pilats</hi> beames alone vncontrolled, but the moate of the Diſciples for gathering a fewe eares of corne on the Sabboth, much complained of and condemned. 5 They are full of all crueltie, vnder the colour of ſimplicitie &amp; innocencie. And herein they are like vnto Woolues in ſheepes cloathing, euer in ſhewe voyde of harmefulneſſe, whereas indeed if they bee vncaſed, they are full of all miſchiefe and crueltie. Beware of theſe men, that you be not deceiued by them: and as one ſayth:
<q>
                  <l>Nunquam te fallant animi ſub vulpe latentes.</l>
                  <l>Impia ſub dulci melle venena latent.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <l>Let not the ſubtill ſleights of Foxe thee vndermine:</l>
            <l>For poiſon lieth hid, in ſweete and honied wine.</l>
            <p>And herewithall agreeth the ſaying of Saint <hi>Bernard, Crede mihi ſub habitu religionis, reperies cor peruerſum.</hi> Beleeue me, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the forme of Religion, thou ſhalt find a peruerſe heart. A Woolfe in a ſheepes skinne ſheweth a dead ſheepe: but that the Woolfe is aliue, it will appeare by his woorkes.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:20"/>A <hi>Nero</hi> within, and a <hi>Cato</hi> without, is a monſter like vnto that Poetical fixion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chimera.</hi> is a three headed. monſter hauing part of the ſhape of a Lion and part of a Dragon. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Leo pars prima, Dracho media ipſa Chimera. Aeneas</hi> neuer hurt the Troians his enemies more, then when he put on armour like vnto theirs, and ſo ruſhed in among his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as one of their ſide. Such hypocrites are the Papiſtical leſuites, who play the diſſembling Gibeonites, pretending that they come from a verie farre countrey for the name of the Lorde our God. Theſe vnder a ſhewe of loue and great care to build vp Hieruſalems Temple with <hi>Nehemia,</hi> ſeeke nothing elſe but the deſtruction thereof. They play the foxe with <hi>Herod,</hi> who pretending a worſhipping of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> practized nothing elſe but to kill him. They haue made <hi>Abſaloms</hi> vowe, vnder the colour of Religion, conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the king and ſtate. And therfore the holy ghoſt ſpeaketh thus vnto them, <hi>I know the blaſphemie of them that ſay they are Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and are not, but are the Sinagogue of ſathan.</hi> Finally, the righteouſneſſe of the Phariſeis was full of preſumption, arrogancie and contempt. For they ſtoode in their owne conceyte, and had a great ouerweening of themſelues, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning all others: as appeareth by that vaine boaſting of that proude Phariſei, who making his prayer in the temple ſayd thus, <hi>O God I thanke thee, that I am not as other men are, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, vniust, adulterers, or as this publican: I fast twiſe in the weeke, I giue tithe of all that euer I poſſeſſe.</hi> This hypocrite is like vnto an Ape, which being no man, but a beaſt, yet he imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth moſt of thoſe things which he ſeeth men doe: Euen ſo this hypocrite counterfeiteth the good workes of Saints, he prayeth, he faſteth, he giueth almes, he payeth tithe of all things: but yet like an Ape. For as the Ape doth he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what, neither doth profite himſelfe by that which he doth: euen ſo theſe kinde of burniſhed and ſmooth fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes do they know not what, becauſe they worke not in faith, being deſtitute of the true loue of God, and of their neighbour. Whereupon <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Omnes ſpecies iuſticia, quas habent ſerui dei in veritate, habere poſſunt ſerui diaboli in ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione.</hi> The children of the diuell may haue in hypocriſie all
<pb facs="tcp:19414:20"/>thoſe tokens of righteouſneſſe, which the ſeruants of God haue in veritie. Theſe hypocrites are like vnto glo-wormes, which although they ſhine in the night, yet in the day they are vncleane and vile wormes. For although hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites ſhine in the night of this worlde through a falſe ſhewe of vertue, yet in the worlde to come they ſhall bee founde foule and abhominable. In the ſayde hypocriticall Phariſei then, we ſee a certaine phantaſticall viſion, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in forme which it hath not in trueth. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> being asked what was moſt effectuall in ſpeaking, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Hypocriſie. Being asked againe the ſecond and thirde time, he anſwered ſtill hypocriſie: meaning thereby, that the whole grace thereof was in ſpeaking, and not in doing. We haue too to manie Rhetoritians in theſe dayes, who can talke and ſpeake well, but do not. They haue their tongues tipt with Religion, as earthen pots are tipt with ſiluer and golde. Theſe haue the cloake whereof <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, and the viſor whereof <hi>Paul</hi> maketh mention. They are the verie ſame of whom Chriſt in the Goſpell ſpeaketh, <hi>This people draweth neere vnto me with their mouthes, and honoureth mee with their lippes, but their hearts are from me.</hi> And againſt whome alſo Chriſt in regard of the abhomination of ſuch hypociſie in his ſight, pronounceth wo againſt the ſame ſeuen times in one Chapter, which is not to bee found in all the Goſpel againſt any other beſides. Hearken therefore to the counſell of the wiſe. <hi>Be not an hypocrite in the ſight of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>1.</hi> Iob. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For the hypocrite ſhall not come bofore God.</hi> God hath not placed men in his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, to bring forth greene leaues onely, but fruit alſo. The figge tree which had nothing but leaues, was accurſed, and withered away by the rootes: the earth which drinketh in the raine that commeth often vpon it, and beareth nothing but thornes and briers, is curſed of God,<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> whoſe end is to be burned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:21"/>
            <head>The fift Leper, is the <hi>proude man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ride is a great loue and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our owne excellencie, and in compariſon of our ſelues, a deſpiſing of others. This leproſie of pride dooth ſundrie waies lay holde vpon men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Semptempliciter occapuit nos lepraſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia, &amp;c.</hi> Wee are (ſaith hee) tainted with the leproſie of pride ſeuen maner of wayes: that is to ſay: in the proprietie of poſſeſſions; in the glorie of apparell; and in the pleaſure of our bodies: Two wayes alſo in our mouth: and two wayes in our heart. In our mouth murmuring in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie; and arrogantly commending our ſelues in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie. In our heart; deſiring to haue our owne will; and following our owne counſaile. Pride (according to her diſpoſition) diſdaineth to go alone, vnwaited vpon, and therefore ſhe is accompanied with many ſinnes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe ſeldome vſeth to go on foote, ſhe hath prepared for her ſelfe a chariot or coach: for ſhe is delicate, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo much the more, becauſe ſhe is vncleane and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous. Her coach is drawne with foure horſes. The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſe is Ambition: the next to him Vaineglorie: the third, Contempt: and the fourth, diſobedience. The foure wheeles, are Boaſting; Arrogancie; Verboſitie, &amp; Leuitie. The coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that driueth and guideth, is the ſpirit of pride. They that accompanie ladie Pride in the coach, are ſuch among all eſtates and degrees, as are proude and vaine in apparell. The horſes before mencioned are vnbrideled, the wheeles moſt ſwift and flying: the driuer and coachman ſelfe-willed and peruerſneſſe, and therefore the ende muſt needs be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. To handle all theſe in particular, would make a larger treatiſe, then at this time I purpoſe: therefore I will
<pb facs="tcp:19414:21"/>but touch three parts: to wit, the beginning, the middeſt, and the end. The beginning, Ambition the middeſt is pride and her companie: the ende is deſtruction whereinto theſe do wilfully run. Ambition is an ouermuch deſire of honour: which honor is that reuerence yelded to any man for a teſtimoniall of his excelencie in good giftes. And a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is giuen vnto him of right: for it is meet that we recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence them with honour, which helpe to preſerue &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vs, being furniſhed with the gifts and graces of God. But they which are honoured muſt eſpecially take heede, that they repoſe not themſelues vpon honour, as vpon the chief end, For whatſoeuer they do, muſt be done of loue, of conſcience &amp; for Gods ſake: &amp; ſpecially that honor which is giuen vnto them to gouerne well: that thereby both them ſelues may knowe and alſo may teach others to glorifie God, and not men in their woorkes. Furthermore they muſt take heed that they be not ſo inflamed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, as that they ſeeke to attaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by vnlawful means. Concerning the which matter, <hi>Saluſt</hi> ſpeketh rhus, toe good and the euill doth both alike, deſire to get, honor, glorie, and rule; the one by good meanes: the other wanting good arts, ſtriueth to compaſſe the ſame, by fraude and guile. For, it falleth out many times in this worlde, that men of meane and baſe parentage, attaine to greater dignities, poſſeſſions and riches, then their deſerts and vertues require deſerueing rather blame then any preferment, Like herein to <hi>Abimilech</hi> who purpoſed to himſelfe a kingly power, without any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to gouerne rightly: and therefore endeuoured to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thernnto by deceits and guiles, and not by lawful and iuſt meanes: ſeeming to bee of <hi>Euripides</hi> iudgement, that euen right it ſelfe, is to be violated for dominions ſake. And for this cauſe the ambitious man is euer fearefull, euer warie and circumſpect, leaſt hee ſhould ſpeake that which might diſpleaſe, he couterfeiteth humilitie, feineth honeſtie, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth affabilitie, vſeth all courteſie, honoureth all men, boweth, ſtoopeth, and maketh obeyſance to euerie man: he
<pb facs="tcp:19414:22"/>haunteth open aſſemblies, viſiteth noble men, he riſeth vp, he imbraceth, he praiſeth &amp; flattereth, and is more then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, verefying this poetical ſaying, <hi>Etſi nullus erit puluis, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerem tamen excute nullum:</hi> that is, Mend a fault, where none is. The ambicious man will whine and weepe with <hi>Eſau,</hi> to ſee anie thing to eſcape his fingers, or any man preferred before him. He may rightly be compared to luie, which cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to climbe to the top of the tree, though it be the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt plant. He is like vnto the Spider which will bee in the kings houſe,<note place="margin">Iudg. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and in the verie top of the temple, though he be full of poyſon. And albeit he is but a furres buſh, yet hee will marrie his ſonne to the Cedar of <hi>Libanus.</hi> And good wife <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bede,</hi> though ſhee bee but a fiſhers wife, muſt haue her two ſonnes to ſit in Chriſts kingdome (which ſhe deemed to be of this world) the one on his right hand, and the other on his left. Like vnto her grandmother <hi>Eue,</hi> who being Queene of the whole world, and ladie of Paradice, yet muſt needes be Goddeſſe <hi>Eue. Balaam</hi> thinketh his Aſſe neuer goeth faſt inough, when he rideth for preferment. And when the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicious man is preferred and exalted, he is alſo therewithall puffed vp in pride, and beginneth to boaſt, he careth not to profit, but reioiceth that he is preferred: he preſumeth that he is the better, becauſe he ſeeth himſelfe ſuperiour: hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth his old friends, and knoweth not his acquaintance: he fawneth vpon ſtrangers, and contemneth his familiars: he talketh of great matters, and meditateth of high things: he canot any longer abide to be ſubiect,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.</note> but ſeeketh to rule, and with <hi>Abſalom</hi> is male content for a kingdom. In the end he is a burthen to ſubiects that are vnder him, an enemie to all men: he is raſh, troubleſome, grieuous, and importune: Thus pride (as ſayth <hi>Abacuc</hi>) proueth a madneſſe, and as <hi>Paul</hi> termeth it, a frenzie. Yea ſo mad are ambicious men ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, and ſo furious, that they commit murther without reſpect of any kinred. <hi>Caine</hi> being afraide leaſt his brother ſhould haue greater fauour and grace then hee, ſlue him. <hi>Romulus</hi> in like caſe killed <hi>Remus. Domitian</hi> lay in wayte
<pb facs="tcp:19414:22"/>for <hi>Titus. Antonius Caracalla</hi> ſlue his brother <hi>Geta Athalia</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the kings ſeede. <hi>Abimilech</hi> ſlue ſeuentie brethren vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one ſtone. And <hi>Hazael</hi> ſtifled his maiſter <hi>Benhadad.</hi> Our Engliſh Chronicles haue many ſuch like examples, which I ouerpaſſe. But the ende and downfall of ſuch hath euer beene moſt miſerable and wofull. <hi>Paulatim aſcendisti</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi>) <hi>ſed non paulatim deſcendes.</hi> Thou diddeſt aſcende by little and little, but thou ſhalt not ſo come downe. For as the Crowe, when ſhe cannot cracke a Nut, flieth a loft, that ſo by the greater fall it may bee broken: euen ſo God many times, ſuffereth proude men to bee placed in high degree in this worlde, that their downefall may bee the greater. Who ſo ſayeth <hi>Regnabo,</hi> I will reigne, (with the proude bremble) or, <hi>Non mouebor,</hi> I ſhall not bee remooued: or, <hi>Quis aſcendet ſuper me?</hi> Who ſhall aſcende aboue mee? Nay though hee ſay nothing, but in his heart receyueth the applauſe of the people, as did <hi>Herod: Deycietur ad imum:</hi> He ſhall be caſt downe to the ground. Therefore the Lorde ſayth, <hi>The pride of thy heart hath deceyued thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>though thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest make thy neast as high as the Eagle, I will bring thee downe from thence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A heathen man beeing asked, what God did in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, anſwered, he did nothing but tumble downe prowde men, and ſet vp humble men. For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayeth,<note place="margin">Pro. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore destruction goeth pride, and before glorie goeth lowlineſſe.</hi> If men were not like vnto children in vnderſtanding, they woulde not ſo greedilie as they doe ſeeke after worldly honour and promotion. It is the faſhion of children to eſteeme more of a painted trifle, then of a rich Iewell: and ſuch is the painted dignitie of this worlde, gotten with much labour, mainteyned with great expences, and ſoone loſt againe with heart-breake and ſorrowe. Let a man recount with himſelfe, if there bee anie ſtate of dignitie which hee coulde wiſh to himſelfe, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men haue not had long ſince. Let him remember howe they mounted vp, and how they deſcended downe againe:
<pb facs="tcp:19414:23"/>and then he may imagine with himſelfe, which was greater, either the ioy in getting, or the ſorrow in forgoing that wherein they ſo much delighted. Where are nowe all thoſe Emperours, thoſe kings, thoſe princes, and prelates, which reioiced ſo much once at their owne aduancement? Where are they now, I ſay, who thinketh or talketh of them? Are they not forgotten and caſt into the graue long ago? And do not men boldly walke ouer their heads now, whoſe faces might not be looked on wihout feare in this world? What then haue their dignities done them good? Honour then is like a mans owne ſhadow, which the more he runneth after, the more it flieth: and when he flieth from it, it followeth him againe, and the onely way to catch it, is to fall downe vpon the ground vpon it. So we ſee that thoſe men which deſired honour in this world, are now forgotten: and thoſe which fled from it, and caſt themſelues loweſt of all men by humilitie, are now moſt of all honoured: honoured, I ſay, moſt by the world it ſelfe, whoſe enemies they were while they liued. For who is honoured more nowe, who is more commended, then the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who ſomuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed worldly honour in this life. Moſt vaine then is the purſute of this worldly honor and promotion, ſeeing it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contenteth the minde, nor continueth with the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, nor is voide of great daungers, both in this life, and in the life to come.</p>
            <p>But now to ſpeake of the brauerie of pride,<note place="margin">Pride.</note> and of her vaine companie. Ye ſhall vnderſtand that Pride (as is ſayd afore) is neuer alone, but accompanied with many vices, being the roote of all euill, and the Queene of all wickednes: and to ſpeake plainely, ſhee is the beginning, the ende, and the cauſe of all ſinnes. When Pride hath gotten the vpper hand and rule of any man or woman, ſhee will not eaſily forſake her vaſſall, but will holde and keepe them, euen as kings doe thoſe caſtels which they haue once conquered and woonne.<note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>10.</hi> Iſai. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> But why is earth and aſhes proude? Let the proude man looke to the rocke out of the which he was cut,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:23"/>and to the pit whence hee was digged. If proude perſons would conſider their beginning and their ende, and if they would continually haue the ſame before there eyes, they ſhould not ſo exceedingly ſinne in pride, as they doe at this day. Was there euer any age from the firſt beginning of the world, ſo far ouergrowne in pride, as this our age? I am well aſſured no. Is there any nation at this day vpon the face of the earth, comparable to vs in this abhominable ſinne of pride? Our exceſſe in apparell will ſay no, wherein both men and women of all eſtates and degrees, from the hieſt to the loweſt, euen from the Courtier to the Carter, doe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly offend. Seruants are in their apparell more coſtlie then many maiſters and dames: yeomen, and yeomens ſonnes are herein equall with gentlemen of good worſhip: poore and meane Gentlemen, compare with Lords: Lords with Kings; and Ladies with Queenes. What will become hereof at the laſt? Where is nowe that moderation in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell which was vſed in king <hi>William Rufus</hi> dayes! who (as Chronicles record) being exceeding ſumptuous in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and hauing a paire of breeches in a morning brought vnto him by his chamberlaine, hee demaunded what they coſt. The chamberlaine anſwered, that they coſt three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Wherewith the king being wroth ſaid: Away beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that thou art, bring me a paire that coſt a Marke. Then the chamberlaine brought vnto the King a paire which coſt much leſſe then a Mark, making the King notwithſtanding beleeue that they were of ſuch price as he deſired: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the king was well pleaſed. But ſuch is the pride of men in theſe dayes, that euery baſe ſeruing man, will diſdaine that now, which king <hi>William</hi> in his exceſſe then, was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed to weare. A wonderfull alteration in a few gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Pride in a king, is a great offence in the ſight of God: but in a poore man, it is one of the three things which God moſt extreemly hateth. <hi>Si vix tolleretur, diues ſuperbus</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>) <hi>pauperem ſuperbum quis ferat?</hi> If a proud rich man be ſcarely tollerable, who can endure a poore man
<pb facs="tcp:19414:24"/>proude? do we not ſee that manie things of great price, as veluet, ſattin, gold and ſiluer lace, fine cambricke, and ſuch like coſtly things are now worne of very meane perſons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of God and man, againſt al common wealth, and contrary to all good example of our forefathers, which things rather belong to princes and to peeres of the lande, then to meane ſubiects. As men and women exceed in the ſubſtance of apparrell, ſo alſo in the forme they daily ſhewe forth theyr abhominable pride in their inconſtancie. For no colour, forme or faſhion long contenteth them. We one while imitate the Spaniard, another while the French: one while the Italian another while the Dutch. Euery nation is a ſeuerall patterne for vs. We are like vnto <hi>Camlepardus,</hi> who beeing but one beaſt, repreſenteth the figure and ſhape of many. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Chamelion.</hi> which changeth into euery colour laide before him. Let theſe proude peacocks remember to what end apparrel was appointed by God at the firſt, verily for a couering to hide our ſhame.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Whoſo then is proude of apparrell giuen to this end, is as if a theefe ſhould be proud of his halter which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince giueth him to weare in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance of his pardon. <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſeeing a man to haue a great pride in his clothes, ſayd vnto hym, be not ſo proude man, a ſhepe wore that cote before thee. What vanitie is it then for vs to be ſo curious in apparrell, and to take ſuch pride there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as we do. We rob and ſpoile all creatures almoſt of the world to couer our backes, and to adorne our bodies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. From ſome we take their wooll: from many their skins: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers theyr furres: from ſundrie, their verie excrements as the ſilke, which is nothing elſe, but the verie excrement of the wormes. Not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with this; we come to fiſhes, &amp; do beg of them certaine pearles to hang about vs: we go down into the ground for golde and ſiluer, and turne vp the ſands of the ſea for precious ſtones. And hauing borrowed all this of other creatures, we iet vp and downe, prouoking men to looke vppon vs, as if all this now were our owne. When the ſtone ſhineth vpon our finger, we will ſeeme forſooth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:19414:24"/>to ſhine. When the ſiluer and ſilkes doe gliſter on our backes, we looke bigge, as if all that beautie came from vs. It is reported of that holie father <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that when hee ſawe a woman apparelling and decking of herſelfe in prowde attire, with gorgeous array, hee wept: and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demaunded of the cauſe why hee did ſo, becauſe (ſayth he) all this preparation is for her owne deſtruction. And one <hi>Pambus</hi> in the like action, made the ſame anſwere at an other time: as appeareth in the 8. booke and ſecond chapt. of the tripertite hyſtorie. But our nice and mincing dames in England, whoſe whole life is ſpent for the moſt part in ſtudie, in care, and in practize, to decke, paint, and beautiſie themſelues, wil hardly be perſwaded by <hi>Pambus,</hi> or by <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> that they beſtow this great coſt vpon themſelues, to their owne deſtruction. And though the Lorde himſelfe hath ſaid in his worde. <hi>The woman ſhall not weare mans apparell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>neither ſhall a man put on womans raiment: for all that do ſo are an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination to the Lord:</hi> Yet for all this prohibition, manie wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in theſe dayes weare doublets, and breeches (though peraduenture by them otherwiſe termed) garments for the faſhion appertaining to men. Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his booke <hi>de Velandis virginibus,</hi> ſaith, that the diuell himſelfe was the firſt inuenter of ſuch painting, frizling, and gorgeous decking. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> hauing written of womans attyre, condemneth the vanitie which they vſe in attiring of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, affirming that through their pride herein, they tempt men, and open a way to luſt, which ſhould be ſhut. Beſide this, they do ſeeke to controll and amend the workemanſhip of God in their creation, by adding vnto their bodies and faces a forme and faſhion, which he hath not giuen vnto them. A Painter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made an artificiall peece of worke after his beſt skill, if an other man come after him, and doe trace the ſame with other colours and lineaments, will take it to bee done to controll his workmanſhip, whereat he much diſdaineth: Euen ſo, ſeeing God hath faſhioned our bodies after his owne minde, he deteſteth and cannot abide counterfeiting
<pb facs="tcp:19414:25"/>and ſtraunge colours: as in ſtead of blacke or browne haire which he hath naturally giuen vnto thee, to weare the haire of another bodie, which they call periwigs, or to die thine owne with Saffron, or ſuch like colour: for in ſo doing thou takeſt vpon thee to controll and correct Gods skill and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in thy creation: the which to do muſt needs bee abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in his ſight. On which wickednes the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by the mouth of the prophet to take vengeance after this maner,<note place="margin">The ende of Pride.</note> ſaying, Becauſe the daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> are haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and walke with ſtretched out necks, and with wandring eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their feet, therefore ſhall the Lord make the heads of the daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> bauld, and the Lord ſhall diſcouer their ſecret parts.<note place="margin">Iſai. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> In that day ſhall the Lord take away the ornament of the Pantofles or Slippers, and the Cauls, and the round tiers, the ſweet Pomanders, and the Bracelets, and the Bonets, the tiers of the heade, and the ſloppes, the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and the Tablets, and the Earrings, the Rings and the Mufflers, the coſtly apparell &amp; the vailes, and the wimples, and the criſping pinnes, and the glaſſes, and the fine linnen, and the hoods, and the lawnes. And in ſtead of ſweet ſauour, there ſhall be ſtinke; and in ſtead of a girdle a rent; and in ſtead of dreſſing the haire, baldneſſe; and in ſtead of a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macher a girding of ſackcloth, and burning in ſtead of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This vengeance of God in this maner threatned, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what ſhall be the ende of pride. Forſake then this vanitie with ſpeede, and imbrace humilitie. For though thou be as rich as <hi>Naball,</hi> as beautifull as <hi>Abſhalom,</hi> or faire <hi>Suſanna:</hi> and for braue apparell, as gallant as thoſe of whom <hi>Iſai</hi> maketh mention, yet if thou be not humble thou art no bodie. This one ſentence, <hi>He caſteth downe the proude, and exalteth the humble and meeke,</hi> is repeated twelue times in the old teſtament, and ſeuen times in the new, to teach vs how deteſtable a thing pride is, &amp; how acceptable a thing humility is in gods ſight. God ſpared <hi>Herod</hi> when he perſecuted his Saints, when hee ſlue <hi>Iohn Baptist:</hi> but hee ſtroke him with a mortall plague
<pb facs="tcp:19414:25"/>when he was proude: to ſhewe, that God hateth a proude man, more then any other. Humilitie, although blemiſhed with manie ſinnes in the Publican, yet is it allowed of God. But pride, accompanied with manie vertues in the Phariſei, is reiected and abhorred. Pride ouerthrew the loftie tower of <hi>Babell,</hi> confounded the language, proſtrated <hi>Goliah,</hi> hung vp <hi>Haman,</hi> killed <hi>Antiochus,</hi> drowned <hi>Pharach,</hi> and ſlue <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib.</hi> Yea pride, hath cauſed God to ouerthrow the ſeats of proud captaines, to drie vp the rootes of proud nations. To conclude, Pride caſteth downe headlong, from the higheſt heauens vnto the bottomles deepe: and Humilitie lifteth vp on high. The one caſt downe an Angel from heauen to hell: and the other exalteth a man from earth to heauen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſixt Leper, is the <hi>Glutton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Glutton is he, whoſe bellie is his God: as if he liued to no other ende then to eate and drinke. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the miſerable man deceiueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For in deede God hath giuen to no man life, to eat, but permitteth him to eate, that hee may liue vnto God. Meates are ordained for the bellie, and the bellie for meats,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> but God ſhal deſtroy both it and them. This Gluttonie was the ſpirituall leproſie of thoſe foure lepers,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.</note> which abode by the gate of Samaria, and went to the enemies campe to eate and to drinke. For as thoſe men came to the tents of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in deſperate maner to fill themſelues; euen ſo all they which ſeruing not God but their bellie, being alſo careleſſe of eternall life, ſeeme to ſay, <hi>Let vs eate and drinke, to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> The Glutton to maintaine his bellie cheare, is bold to alledge for himſelfe, the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>That to the cleane all things are cleane:</hi> and that the good creatures of God
<pb facs="tcp:19414:26"/>are not to be refuſed, but to be receyued with giuing of thanks. True it is, that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatures of god are good in their kind, ſo as they be taken in conuenient time, and in meaſure, but glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which obſerue neither meaſure, nor time, in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſpoiling the good creatures of God, are through their beaſtly appetite, vncleane. For as <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſayth, <hi>non ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed appetitus in vitio est.</hi> Not the meate but the appetite is in fault. <hi>Eſau</hi> was reprehended for a meſſe of pottage, whereas <hi>Elias</hi> did eate fleſh without reprehenſion: <hi>Adam</hi> was not condemned for eating fleſh but an apple: and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> gaue fleſh to angels, and it was accepted. Therefore not that which goeth into the man defileth the man.<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayth <hi>Ciborum libertas conceſſa est ſed non luxuriandi.</hi> The libertie of meates is granted, but not of ſurfetting, and Gurmandize. No creature is pure, but they abuſe thereof may cauſe it to turne to our deſtruction. For although hee which gathered the leaſt quantitie of Manna, had no lacke, yet ſome kept more then was appointed by God, whereuppon it corrupted, ſtunke, and was full of wormes.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>There may be alleaged many reaſons to perſwade vs to temperance in meats and drinks. Firſt, becauſe a temperate diet doth continue vs in health, whereas gluttonie and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting filleth the bodie with many diſeaſes. For nature is vniform in her operation, &amp; is then hindred in her digeſtion when ſhe is ſurcharged with ſundery meates and drinkes, the which, as they be of ſeuerall qualities, ſo ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are ſooner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cocted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherſome, which bringeth corruption to the ſtomack hereupon the wiſe man giueth vs this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, as an expert phiſition, ſaying, <hi>Be not greedie in all delights and be not too haſtie in all meates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For exceſſe of meats bringeth ſicknes, and gluttonie turneth into Cholericke diſeaſes. By ſurfeit haue many periſhed but he that dieteth him ſelf, prolongeth his life.</hi> A poore man (as we ſee by daily experience) which liueth with a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſpaire diet, hath more aſſured health, and liueth longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that vſeth to feed of many diſhes at one time.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:26"/>Mans nature is more eaſily ſatisfied, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his appetite, which is inſatiable. One wood will containe many elephants: but man is ſcarcely content with the whole earth and ſea. The beginning of mans ſuſtenance was bread &amp; water: but now gluttons are not content, hauing the fruits of the trees, all maner of graine, all rootes of hearbs, all the fiſhes of the ſea, all the beaſtes of the earth, and all the foules of the aire: but they ſeeke for colours to pleaſe their eies, for odoriferous, and aromaticall ſauours and ſmels: they bring vp by hand crammed and franked foules and beaſtes: and that which cannot be fatted by hand they enterlarde. The cookes make experiments and trie their skill: one beateth and compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, another confecteth and confoundeth, conuerting the ſubſtance into accidents, and chaunging nature into atte: that fulneſſe may be turned into hunger, that the appetite may be whetted to gluttonie, not to ſuſtaine nature, not to ſerue neceſſitie, but to fulfill inſaciable gurmandize. And albeit the ſtomach ſheweth it ſelfe to bee filled by often belchings, yet curioſitie is not ſatisfied, but while the eye delighteth in colours, and the palat taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in taſte, the wofull ſtomacke which diſcerneth no colours, nor iudgeth of the reliſh or taſte, being conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to receyue all that is thruſt into it, is rather oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ouerwhelmed, then refreſhed. The heathen were woont to build Temples for their gods, to build al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, to ordaine Miniſters to ſerue, to ſacrifice beaſts, to burne incenſe, and to make a melodious noiſe in that time of ſeruice: euen ſo the Epicures of out time, haue their kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin in ſteade of a Temple: for their God, their bellie: their table is the aultar: their Miniſters are the Cookes: their beaſts for ſacrifice, are their boiled, roſted, and baked meats: their incenſe are their ſweete perfumes: and their melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is the noyſe of viols, Recorders, Cornets, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe may delight all their ſenſes: without regarde of God, or godlineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Another reaſon why we ought to be temperate in our
<pb facs="tcp:19414:27"/>diet is, becauſe Gluttonie bringeth forth another as euill as her ſelfe: that is to ſay, Drunkenneſſe, the daughter of Gluttonie: whereof Chriſt giueth vs this caueat, <hi>Take heede least at any time your hearts be ouercome with ſurfetting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe:</hi> The which <hi>Seneca</hi> calleth a voluntarie madneſſe. The heathen were farre more temperate then we which haue the knowledge of the true God, and profeſſe our ſelues to bee Chriſtians. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, <hi>Recta mente vti non poſſunt, multo vino &amp; cibo repleti.</hi> They which are full of much wine and meate, cannot haue a right vnderſtanding: for it dulleth the mind, and ouerthroweth the wit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And this is a third reaſon, may ſerue to make vs loath Gluttonie For wherein doth a man differ from a brute beaſt but in this, that he hath reaſon, and vnderſtanding, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunke, he is deuoyde of theſe for the time. For as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſayth <hi>Ebrioſus cum putat bibere, bibitur:</hi> The drunken man when he thinketh to drinke, is drunken. So that they can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing rightly, but iudge all things peruerſly. For as their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall eyes are ſo dazeled, that euery ſingle thing ſeemeth vnto them double, and ſtreight things crooked: euen ſo their minde is blinded, that they thinke good to be euill, and euill good. And no maruell, becauſe, as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietas eſt vile ſepulcrum rationis &amp; furor mentis.</hi> Drunkenneſſe is a vile ſepulture of reaſon, and a furor of the minde. Yet wee ſee that common drunkards haue a great delight herein, yea ſo great pleaſure ioyned with pride in this wickedneſſe, that they prouoke others vnto the ſame with chalenges to drinke a carrous. And yet, when theſe haue drunke ſo much as they can, an Aſſe will drinke more, and a barrell will hold more then anie mans bellie. What ſingular thing then doe they in performing this: ſurely no more then an Aſſe can doe, nor ſo much as an emptie caske containe. Nay rather how beaſthke doe they herein ſhew themſelues to be, and much worſe then beaſts. The bruit beaſt cannot be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by any man to drinke when he hath no thirſt: but men are ſo intemperate, that when they are repleate euen to the
<pb facs="tcp:19414:27"/>mouth, yet they will take in more,<note place="margin">Iſai. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> vntill they haue verified the ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>Your tables are full of filthie vomitings, no place is cleane.</hi> Herein they make their bellies worſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols then <hi>Bell,</hi> deuouring without meaſure, that which might ſuſtaine many poore men and women much better then themſelues.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And this is a fourth reaſon, why men ſhould abhorre gluttonie &amp; be temperate, euen for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon good of the brethren. But ſo little care of common wealth is had herein, that rich men do not care what they ſpend, vpon ſuch things as pleaſe their appetite, though in a time forbidden, and of ſuch things as lawe reſtrayneth them. Now a dayes we ſee the appetites of ſome to be ſo curious and nice, that they care not for the fleſh of lambes, except, of the tidieſt that may be gotten: the like nice and wanton appetite they haue to many other things: whereas in the time of the law, God gaue this commaundement to his people,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſeath a kid in his mothers milke:</hi> meaning thereby, that no fruits ſhould beetaken before their due time. Agaynſt this gluttonous appetite which hath more luſt then hunger, the Lord by the mouth of his Prophet ſpeaketh thus, <hi>They eate the lambes of the flockes, and the calues out of the ſtall, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> I ſpeake not this to condemne the moderate vſe of Gods good creatures, giuen for the comfort and ſuſtenance of man, nor againſt the extraordinary prouiſion of feaſts and ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, wherein friends do ſolace and ioy togither in honeſt and godly mirth. For before the lawe, we read, that there was a feaſt made at <hi>Iacobs</hi> mariage: and another vnder the lawe at <hi>Samſons</hi> mariage. In the time of grace, a feaſt was made in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galile,</hi> by occaſion of a mariage whereat Chriſt was preſent and a gueſt. <hi>Matthew</hi> at his conuerſion is ſaid to make a great feaſt, whereunto alſo Chriſt vouchſafed to come: therfore feaſts are lawfull.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> The fatneſſe of the earth ſerueth not for <hi>Eſau</hi> onely, but it is <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſſing to. Quailes appertaine to Gods children. Bees make their honie (as the heathen man ſayth) <hi>Non ſtultis ſolum,</hi> not for fooles onely, but
<pb facs="tcp:19414:28"/>alſo for wiſe men. This onely I wiſhe, that the wine and cates prouided for feaſts and bankets, be not gotten by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, briberie and violence: ſecondly, that our feaſts bee not appointed as ſnares, to catch and betray innocents: ſuch as was <hi>Herods</hi> feaſt on his birth-day, which coſt <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> his head. Such feaſts beginne with milke, and ende with a nail. Such was the mariage feaſt that was appointed in Paris for <hi>Henrie</hi> the French king that now is, where ſome noble men, many gentlemen, and good ſubiects were by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and curſed crue, wofully betraied, &amp; moſt cruelly maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred. Thirdly, that there bee great care had, that in our bankets there be kept a Chriſtian moderation without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Otherwiſe they are verie dangerous, being vſed in that ſuperabundance of delicates, and mirth ful of al ſcurrilitie, as worldly men do vſe them. Such feaſting, &amp; ſuch mirth, with all the gueſts,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt accurſeth, ſaying, <hi>Wo be vnto you which now do laugh, for ye ſhall weepe: wo be vnto you that now liue in fulnes, for the time will come that ye ſhall ſuffer hunger.</hi> In like manner <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaking of Epicures and worldlings, ſayth, that they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace themſelues with all kinde of Muſicke,<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and paſſe ouer their dayes with pleaſure, and in a moment doe go downe into hell. A wiſe trauailer paſſing by his Inne, though hee ſee pleaſant meates offered him, yet hee forbeareth vppon conſideration of the price, and the iourney he hath to make, and taketh in nothing, but ſo much as he knoweth well how to diſcharge the next morning, at his departure. But a foole layeth handes on euerie delicate baite ſet before him, and when it commeth to the reckoning, hee wiſheth that he had liued with bread and drinke onelie, rather then to bee ſo troubled about the payment. Euen ſo the Scripture teacheth vs, that our laughter ſhall bee mingled with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, and mourning ſhall enſue at the ende of mirth. The Diuell that playeth the hoſt in this worlde, and that ſerueth you with what pleaſure and delight ye deſire, writeth vp all in his booke, and at the day of your departure out of this life, will hee bring the whole reckoning, and charge you
<pb facs="tcp:19414:28"/>with the totall ſumme: and then ſhall follow that which God threatneth by <hi>Amos:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Your mirth ſhall be turned to mourning and lamentation.</hi> Yea, &amp; more then this, if ye be not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the reckoning, you may perhaps heare that other dreadfull ſentence of Chriſt in the Reuelation:<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Looke howe much hee hath beene in his delights, ſo much torment doe yee lay vpon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The laſt and maine reaſon of all other, why we ſhould auoide gluttonie and exceſſe, is, becauſe by temperance we are more ſtrong, to reſiſt euill temptations of the diuell, to bridle ſinne, and euery way more apt for the ſeruice of God. For wiſe <hi>Salmon</hi> ſayeth truely, <hi>Qui delicate à puiritia nutrit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum ſuum, postea ſentiet eum contumacem.</hi> He that doth dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie feede his ſeruant (that is to ſay, his bodie) from his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, ſhall in time to come finde him ſtubburne. A pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered horſe will caſt his rider in the mire: and pampered fleſh will caſt the ſoule into the ſinke of ſinne. Who ſo pampereth his bodie, feedeth his enemie. For the fleſh lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth contrarie to the ſpirite,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and the ſpirite contrarie to the fleſh. Gluttonie is the gate by which the Diuell with his whole armie entreth. For as Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſayth, <hi>Quanto corpus impletur, tanto anima minoratur.</hi> By how much the bodie is filled, by ſo much is the ſoule weakned. The Which Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> noteth excellently by a ſimilitude of the Crab, and the Oyſter. The Crab (ſayth he) loueth to feede on the oiſter fiſh, but becauſe they are ſo ſtrongly incloſed in their ſhels, that by his ſtrength he cannot get them out, hee doth craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily watch them vntill they open themſelues againſt the Sunne: then taketh he a ſmall ſtone, and putting it into the gaping Oiſter, that he cannot cloſe vp himſelfe againe, hee eaſily conueyeth in his clawe, and ſo feedeth on the fiſh at his pleaſure: Euen ſo, when men hauing filled their bellies, do giue themſelues to eaſe, and to enlarge their minds to all pleaſure, the diuel commeth &amp; conueieth into them al filthy cogitations, whereby he eaſily deuoureth &amp; deſtroieth them. Belly cheare and idlenes, are the bellowes of concupiſcence,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:29"/>the which bellowes haue kindled ſo great and ſo hot a fire, as it is to be feared, will not be quenched, till all be conſumed with the laſt fire. The onely corporall remedie and meane to quench this fire,<note place="margin">Faſting.</note> is abſtinence, to moſt men and women in theſe dayes vnknowne: except to the poorer ſort, who more by penurie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of deuotion are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to faſt. This libertie is come to paſſe two wayes. Firſt by the neglecting and not executing of ſuch lawes and orders as are well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for appointed faſts amongſt vs. The which contempt, as it diſpleaſeth god, ſo alſo it is a great hurt to the common wealth, and will (without ſpeedie remedie) bee more felt hereafter. Secondly, by the vndiſcrete dealing of ſome tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, more hot and raſh, then wiſe, who in ſpeaking againſt ſuperſticious faſting, haue not taught the people to vſe anie faſt at all. And they on the other ſide, being euer readie to fall into extremities, do not onely neglect godly faſts, ſuch as by lawe are appoynted, being ignorant of their right and true vſe, but do alſo condemne them as ſuperſtitious and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh. Whereas if they once rightly vnderſtood the benefite of ſuch faſts truely vſed, redounding both to bodie and ſoule, they would gladly vſe them more often then they doe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as haue any care to ſerue and pleaſe God. Faſting doth greatly tame the rebellion of fleſhly luſts. For, <hi>Sine corere &amp; Bacche, friget Venus:</hi> By ſpare diet luſt is quenched. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwiſe, <hi>Venter mero astuans, ſpumat libidinem.</hi> The bellie boyling with wine, and daintie faire, fometh out luſt, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſayeth. The earth the fatter it is made with mucke and compoſt, the more weedes and thiſtles it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorth: euen ſo the more our fleſh is pampered with meates and drinkes, the more prone it is to ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Contrariwiſe abſtinence purgeth the minde, lightneth the ſenſes, maketh the fleſh ſubiect to the ſpirite, diſperſeth the cloudes of concupiſcence, extinguiſheth the heate of luſts, and kindleth the light of chaſtitie. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> know how neceſſarie the vſe hereof was for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> and therefore was oftentimes in faſtings. The
<pb facs="tcp:19414:29"/>Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo did put on ſackecloth, and humbled his ſoule with faſting, and therefore ſayth that his prayer retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his boſome with fruit. Faſting is a coadiutor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prayer, making it more feruent,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>34.</hi> Pſal. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> as witneſſeth Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Ieiunium orationem roborat: oratio ſanctificat ieiunium, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentat domino.</hi> Faſting maketh praier more ſtrong: praier ſanctifieth faſting, and preſenteth it before the Lorde. The example of the children of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Iudg. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> of whom a great number being ſlaine by the Beniamits, fitting vpon the ground and faſting, weeping and praying vnto the Lord, maketh this more manifeſt. Furthermore of ſo great force is faſting and prayer, that they both being ioyned togither are able to caſt foorth one ſort of Diuels. It appeareth both in the olde and new teſtament, that faſting was ſo much in vſe, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and holy men then and long ſince, tooke no great matter in hand, but firſt they withdrewe themſelues, from all worldly impediments, faſting and praying. When Gods lawe was deliuered by <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto the people, he faſted for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes and fortie nights. <hi>Elias</hi> alſo at the reſtauration of the lawe, did the like. And Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> writeth, that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ſaint <hi>Iohn,</hi> would not take the writing of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall ſtorie in hande, vntill the Church had commended his purpoſe to God by a faſt. Alſo <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> faſted, before hee confounded <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt himſelfe, entred into a faſt before hee was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and beganne to execute his office. Whoſe example <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> following, commended to the Church the Elders which they had ordained,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> after they had prayed and faſted.</p>
            <p>There was neuer more neede of this Chriſtian exerciſe then nowe, both in reſpect of our owne priuate neceſſities, and alſo in regarde of the manifolde perils, wherein wee all generallie ſtande, our ſinnes daylie prouoking the wrath of God agaynſt vs. It is high time therefore to hearken to the proclamation which the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> maketh, ſaying, <hi>Turne you to the Lord with all your hearts, with fasting weeping and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19414:30"/>mourning. Not in ſuch counterfeit faſting as we haue a long time vſed, which may rather be called <hi>Permutatio da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium terrestrium cum aquatilibus,</hi> then <hi>ieiunium.</hi> That is, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of earthly cates, for them of the water, then a faſt. A right and well ordered faſt ſuch as the holy fathers haue vſed is, to abſtaine wholely from all meates (ſo farre forth as our nature may well indure) all that time of our godly and holy purpoſe ſeruing the Lorde with that ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeruice, which we ſhall take in hand. And here withall we muſt ioine true repentance, making reſtitution of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wronges done to our brethren: and muſt alſo geue almes to the poore and needy: the which is one cauſe of our faſting. For as Saint Auguſtine ſaith, <hi>faſting without almes deeds, is as a lampe without oile.</hi> And Saint <hi>Gregory, This faſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, if thou giue that to the poore, which thou ſpareſt from thy ſelfe.</hi> O that men would put this in practiſe more often then they do, ſo ſhould they not onely fortifie their ſoules againſt many temptations, but alſo procure vnto their bodies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired health, and long life. For I am verily perſwaded, that among men, mo die of ſurfeits, then by any other diſeaſe beſides. If then ye haue no care of your ſoules good, yet at the leaſt, regard the health of your bodies, for the which the rich and welthie do willingly geue large ſummes of mony to the bodily phiſition, which well deſerueth it. Yea, what is he, that for the health of his bodie, will not giue all that he hath Regard then my counſell which I dare aſſure you, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt learned, and moſt experienced Doctors of phiſicke, which haue liued in any age, do allow and ratifie: who with a generall conſent affirme, that moderate abſtinence conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuperfluous humours in the bodie, making the ſame of good and beautifull colour, and that it not onely preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſickeneſſe, but alſo where ſickeneſſe is entred, nothing helpeth ſooner, if it be vſed in due ſeaſon. It prepareth alſo a good appetite after a ſurfeit, and maketh good diſgeſtion, helping Nature to disburden it ſelfe of repletion. <hi>Daniel</hi> and his companions eating pulſe, and drinking water (for a
<pb facs="tcp:19414:30"/>time) were in better liking, then all the children that fared deliciouſly of the kings allowance. <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention of a certaine prince, which neuer roſe vp from his meate with a full ſtomacke, but rather with a good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: which diet as the ſtorie teſtifieth, made him to liue ſo long, as is ſcarce credible to be tolde. This let vs knowe from our Sauiour Chriſt the beſt Phiſition, <hi>That man liueth not by bread onely, but by the worde of God,</hi> by whoſe benediction the creatures giue nouriſhment. The abſtinence whereof I haue ſpoken, muſt be moderate. For when the Apoſtle ſayth he dorh chaſtice his bodie to bring it into ſubiection, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, not to kill our bodies by too much ſtraitneſſe of life. There is a difference betweene chaſtizing and killing. For through vnmeaſurable abſtinence, the moyſture of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is dried vp, the bodie waxeth leane, naturall heate will bee too much inflamed and diſtempered, which ſpeedilie bringeth <hi>Hecticam febrem,</hi> the feuer Cathicke, or conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore <hi>Hypocrates</hi> ſayth, that too much abſtinence is for the more part more daungerous, then that which is more abundant. Exceſſes be equall. Too little is as hurtfull as too much. <hi>Timothie</hi> by not drinking wine, did hurt his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: and <hi>Naball</hi> by too much did the ſame. Therefore a meane and a moderate abſtinence is that which I wiſh: to health a friend: to gluttonie and ſurfetting an enimie, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. Theſe great benefites which come to the bodie and ſoule by abſtinence conſidered, and the manifolde grieuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which come to them both by gluttonie, well weighed, I doubt not but euery one, which heretofore hath had but a meane care for either, will henceforth tend them in better ſort, to their owne benefite, and to the good of the Church and common wealth wherein they liue. The which God graunt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:31"/>
            <head>The ſeuenth Leper, is the Adulterer <hi>or Fornicator.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of the greateſt vanities of the world, wherein men and women take great liking, is beautie and fauour: whereof <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh thus,<note place="margin">Prou. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fauour is deceitfull, and beautie is a vaine thing.</hi> The which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, when he ſayd,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Turne away mine eyes O Lord, that they beholde not vanitie.</hi> Beautie is by holy men, compared vnto a painted ſnake, which is faire without, and full of deadly poyſon within. If a man knewe what fowle droſſe lieth vnder a faire skinne, he would little bee in loue therewith. If he would call to minde what deſtruction hath come by liking and luſting after the ſame, he would be ware of this vaine and fonde vanitie. The which may rightly bee called fond, for that euerie childe may diſcerne the deceyte and vanitie thereof. For take the faireſt face in the worlde, wherein infinite fooliſh men fall in loue vpon the ſight, and raſe it ouer but with a little ſcratch, and all the matter of loue is gone. Let there come but a feuer, and all this goodlie beautie is deſtroyed. Let the ſoule depart but one halfe houre from the bodie, and this louing face is grieſly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant to looke vpon: let it lie but two dayes in the graue, and thoſe which were ſo hot in loue with it before, will ſcarce abide to beholde it, or come neere it. And if none of thoſe things happen vnto it: yet quickly commeth on olde age, which wrinckleth the skinne, draweth in the eyes, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out the teeth, and ſo diſguiſeth and disfigureth the whole viſage, as it becommeth more contemptible nowe, then it was beautifull and alluring before. And what then can be more vanitie then this? What more madneſſe, then either to be proude of it to ſee it in thy ſelfe, or to indanger thy ſoule for it when thou ſeeſt it in others, and lookeſt too
<pb facs="tcp:19414:31"/>narrowly vpon it luſting after it? For the occaſion of the hearts luſt is the eye: the which is called by the ſchoolemen concupiſcence: and the luſt of the eye ſenſualitie: of both which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> writeth in his Epiſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.</note> calling the one the luſt of the fleſh, and the other the luſt of the eyes. The holy man <hi>Iob</hi> knowing the daunger that might come by the luſt of the eye, ſayth thus, <hi>I haue made a couenant with mine eyes, that I would not looke on a virgin.</hi> This ſence of ſeeing, as it is moſt forcible to moue, ſo it is moſt forcible to moue to ſinne. Wherefore a <hi>Rabbine</hi> ſayth, The eye is the broker of the heart to all ſinne. The beginning of which brokage is to bee ſeene in <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> in the talke betwixt the Serpent and the woman: <hi>she ſeeing the tree to be faire and beautifull.</hi> Whervpon it is noted, that the eye effended, before the apple went downe her throte. The eye wrought firſt in <hi>Achab</hi> the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueting of <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard. It made <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Sichem</hi> to ſin. We haue a common ſaying amongſt vs, Let vs go and ſee; to ſee is no harme. This is a great ſtratageme of the diuell, to perſwade vs, there is no daunger in that, which may moſt intangle vs. For by this meanes the diuell tempted Chriſt, to ſhewe him all the kingdomes of the world. This then is the firſt thing in vs that muſt be mortified, to keepe thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leprous and filthie ſinne of whordome, to wit, <hi>If thine eye offend thee plucke it out,</hi> that is to ſay: Make a conſcience of thy lookes. Otherwiſe we ſhall be tempters of our ſelues. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the which Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeaketh thus. <hi>Quid prodest à deo petere ne inducat in tentationem, cum tu teipſum inducas.</hi> What dooth it profite thee to deſire of God not to lead thee into temptation, when as thou leadeſt thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Concerning whordome. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the choſen veſſell of God writeth thus to the <hi>Corinthians. Flie from whordome. Al the ſinnes that a man doth are without his bodie: but who ſo committeth whordome ſinneth against his owne bodie.</hi> And a little before the Apoſtle expreſſeth the vnderſtanding of this ſentence, and ſayth, <hi>Know ye not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt? Shall I then take Christs members, and make them the members of a harlot?
<pb facs="tcp:19414:32"/>God forbid.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> then, when he ſpake theſe wordes (<hi>All the ſinne that a man doth, &amp;c.</hi> had reſpect vnto matrimonie. For like as wedlocke maketh of two perſons one bodie: euen ſo likewiſe the ſpiritual mariage, namely the receiuing of Gods grace, in that we are baptized into Chriſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth one bodie betweene Chriſt and vs, in ſuch wiſe, that we be called, and are in deede, Chriſt his members. Nowe then he that is maried, if hee take another beſide his wife, doth ſinne, not onely againſt his wife, but alſo againſt his owne body, in committing woordome. For he diſhououreth the grace of Chriſt, and defileth the holy couenant made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and him. For the Apoſtle addeth this to that which is alreadie ſpoke, <hi>Know ye not that he which ioyneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a harlot is become one bodie? But whoſo cleaueth vnto the lorde is one ſpirit.</hi> Neuertheleſſe through wordome is the ſpirit ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and excluded. For thy ſpirit, heart, and minde that ought to cleaue vnto the Lorde, is ioyned to the harlot, with whom thou art one, and incorporated. Therefore they that do commit wordom, do ſinne againſt the couenant and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall mariage, whereby wee muſt bee ioyned into Chriſt Furthermore it followeth in the Apoſtle, <hi>Or know ye not that your bodies are the Temple of the holie ghoſt which is in you, whome yee haue of God, and that yee are not your owne? fot yee are dearely bought.</hi> Whereby it muſt needes follow, that they which commit whordome, doe diſhonour their bodies, giuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their members, and their heart and mind to vncleannes, Whereas Chriſt that he might bee honoured in vs, and to make vs cleane, hath redeemed our bodies, not with monie, but with his moſt precious bloud. O extreame filthineſſe of luſt, which doth not only effeminate the mind, but doth alſo weaken the bodie: which doth not only pollute the ſoule, but alſo defile the perſon: before the which there goeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way burning heate &amp; wantonnes, with it ſtinke &amp; vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and euer following it griefe and repentance. It is that fire whereof holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> a fire that ceaſeth not till it hath conſumed quite and cleane: not kindled by God, but
<pb facs="tcp:19414:32"/>by the diuell. For as a Smith when he cannot frame his iron to the faſhion he would haue it, putteth the ſame into the fire, and bloweth till it be hot, and then bringeth it to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile: euen ſo the diuell, when he cannot bring a man to ſuch ſinnes as he deſireth, he maketh him hot with the fire of luſt, that ſo he may make him pliant to the ſinne of whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Theſe men whom the diuell thus worketh, are, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth vnder the wrath and vengeance of God: For he ſayth, that <hi>our bodyes are the temples of the holy Ghost:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>but</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>if any man defile the temple of God, him will God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy.</hi> Is it not an horrible defiling of Gods temple for that vicious idoll harlot <hi>Venus,</hi> to bee euen in the place, where God ſhould reigne with his ſpirite, and for men to bee ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with her, and to doe her ſeruice both with bodie and ſoule? Let them now come forth that liſt to excuſe ſingle fornication, as if it were no ſinne. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle of Chriſt ſayeth, that whordome diuideth vs from God, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the couenant which we haue with God, ſpoyleth and robbeth God of that which is his, diſordereth the members of God, maketh of Chriſts members, the members of a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, defyleth and vnhalloweth the temple of God, for the which God threatneth deſtruction. If all this be to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med but a ſmall thing, then do I confeſſe, that whordom and fornication, is ſo ſmal a ſinne, as vicious and vaine people do ſeeke to make it.<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>2.</hi> Corinth. <hi>5.</hi> Gal. <hi>5.</hi> Ephe. <hi>5.1.</hi> Theſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> It is more then once that whoremongers are threatned to be ſhut out of the kingdome of heauen, as plainely appeareth in <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtles. And the Athour to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> ſayth plainlie, that God will iudge whoremongers and adulterers. The which iudgement beginneth manie times in this worlde to ſhewe forth it ſelfe vpon the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in this wickedneſſe. This ſubuerted the Cities of Sodom and Gomorha, and the Countrey there about, and ſlue <hi>Sichem</hi> with his people: This wounded the ſonnes of <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſtabbed the Iewe, and the Madianitiſh woman, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen through the bodies of them both togither: this deſtroied the tribe of <hi>Beniamin</hi> for the Leuites wife: proſtrated the
<pb facs="tcp:19414:33"/>ſonnes of <hi>Hely</hi> the Prieſt in the battell. This killed <hi>Vrias,</hi> ſlue <hi>Aman,</hi> and ſtoned many to death. This curſed <hi>Ruben,</hi> ſeduced <hi>Samſon,</hi> and peruerted <hi>Salomon.</hi> This approueth that to bee true which is written. <hi>Through the beautie of women manie haue periſhed.</hi> What ſhould I ſpeake of the diſeaſes which come through the filthineſſe of this ſinne vpon many men, yea vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that fall into it, as Goutes, Palſeis, Pockes, Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and filthie lothſome leprocies, the iuſt plagues of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God for the ſame. The which maketh Saint <hi>Herom</hi> to breake forth into this exclamation, <hi>O ignis infernalis luxuria, cuius materia gula, cuius flamma ſuperbia, cuius ſcintilla praua colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia, cuius fumus infamia, cuius cinis immundicia, cuius finis gehenna.</hi> O Lecherie the infernal fire, the maker whereof is gluttonie, whoſe flame is pride, whoſe ſparkes are vnclean words, and filthie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, whoſe ſmoke is infamie, whoſe aſhes is vncleanneſſe, whoſe end is hell fire. And in another place, <hi>O how grieuous are the fruits of lecherie, more bitter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaul, and more wounding then a ſword.</hi> Beſide theſe puniſhments which whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers bring vpon themſelues, they alſo incurre the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, and correction of the Magiſtrate, who is appointed to puniſh the ſame, and ſuch like offences. For whordome hath euer beene taken for an abhomination among all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people in the whole world: inſomuch that all vertuous rulers, yea heathen Magiſtrates, hath euer puniſhed the ſame, yea euen with the paine of death. In the law of God it is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſo committeth adulterie with any mans wife, ſhall die the death, both the man and the woman, becauſe hee hath broken wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke with his neighbors wife.</hi> Neither was adulterie ſo ſore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed among the children of Iſrael onely, but alſo among the heathen. When anie of the <hi>Lepreians</hi> were taken in adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, they were bound, and caried three dayes through the city, and afterward ſo long as they liued they were deſpiſed, and with ſhame and confuſion reputed as perſons deſtitute of all honeſtie. Among the <hi>Locrenſians, Zaleucus</hi> forbad adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie vnder the paine of a ſore puniſhment: cauſing the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors to haue both their eyes put out. And when his owne
<pb facs="tcp:19414:33"/>ſonne was taken in adulterie, his people ſuing verie earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his pardon, he did put out one of his owne eyes, and an other of his ſonnes: by that meanes leauing to his ſonne the vſe of his ſight, and yet to the terror of his ſubiects, not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring example to bee giuen of the breach of his law without iuſt puniſhment. In old time the Germans before they came to the Chriſtian faith, gaue the full power and authoritie of puniſhing a woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brake wedlocke, to her husband: who at the leaſt might ſtrip her out of her clothes, thruſt her out of his houſe, and beat her openly with roddes in the citie or towne before her friends: whereof <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> maketh mention. <hi>Opilius Macronius</hi> Emperour of Rome (as <hi>Iulius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitolinus</hi> recordeth) vſed to puniſh adulterers with fire, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them that were taken in adulterie to bee bound, and to be burnt together quicke. And among the Romans there was a common law (called <hi>Lex Iulia</hi>) which appointed exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution to be done vpon adulterers with the ſword: the which law was receiued by the chriſtian Emperours. Much more may be ſaide concercerning the puniſhments ordained by magiſtrates (where there hath bene any good gouernment) of this deteſtable ſinne, which peraduenture to ſome will ſeeme verie cruell and rigorous. But if they would conſider the matter aright, ſetting affection and euill cuſtome aſide, and would ponder wel what adultery were, how dangerous and contagious a leproſie, they would not wonder ſo ſore at the puniſhment. For adulterie is a diſhonour done vnto god by violating his holy ordinance, a wickedneſſe ſprung from the diuell, an idleneſſe of the fleſh, a ſhameful vnfaithfulnes, a wilful trucebreaking and periurie. But wedlocke is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinance of God, in the which both the parties ought ſo to bee knit the one to the other that they bee not diuided. Now al maried perſons, when they enter into matrimonie, do make a perpetuall couenant: and calling vpon God, and taking him to record before the whole congregation, they promiſe troth and faith, with mouth and hand, the one to the other. If this then bee but a ſmall treſpaſſe, to diſſemble, to
<pb facs="tcp:19414:34"/>breake, to deſtroy, and to tread vnder foot al this, to forſwear troth giuen before God and the Church, and nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard honeſtie and faith: then muſt I needes confeſſe that the puniſhment of adulterie, was verie rigorous in old time. But if it be a iuſt thing ſeuerely to puniſh vnfaithful periury, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing of God &amp; al honeſtie, then is alſo the puniſhment of adultrie right equal &amp; not to ſore. Moreouer if the loſſe of a good thing, ſhould be valued after the eſtimation of the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then (as touching this life) there is no greater iniurie and damage, then a man to looſe his owne bodie. And moſt ſure it is, that the man and his wife are but one bodie, and that the husband hath no power of his owne bodie but the wife, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the wife power of her own body, but the husband, according to the doctrine of the Apoſtle. Wherefore whoſo committeth adulterie, the ſame taketh away, ſtealeth &amp; rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the other of his owne bodie, euen his principall &amp; beſt good. Or what honeſt perſon had not rather find a theef ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his treaſure, &amp; to ſuffer the loſſe of his goods, then to find an adulterer by his maried ſpouſe, and to reape diſhonour in her. Furthermore, it is to be conſidered, that through adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie great inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are altered, and the right heires diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited. For oftentimes it falleth out that an adultreſſe hath children by an adulterer, which inherit al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of their pretended father as lawfull children, which yet are vnlawfull: whereby the father looſeth his honour, his kinred, his bodie, and his goods. His wife which is his owne bodie hath the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterer defiled, and the vnlawfull children take the goodes away. If this be not great wrong and wickedneſſe, then am lignorant, what a man may affirme to bee vicious enough. Therefore though adulterie be great wickednes both in men and women, yet in women it is moſt hurtful and deteſtable. For beſides that the adulterers altereth the inheritance (as I ſaid before) and with falſhood &amp; ſhameful deceit, withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; ſtealeth it from the right heires, ſhe ladeth firſt her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt poore husband with great ſhame, great trauel, labor, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and pain, in that he is compelled to bring vp thoſe adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous
<pb facs="tcp:19414:34"/>children which are not his own. Moreouer ſhe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth her father, her mother, her kinred, her children (euen her lawfull children, who in time to come will be aſhamed of her) and of whom doubt will be made in the world, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be lawfully begotten or no. Therefore when they ſpeake of their mother, or heare her named, they are abaſhed and aſhamed. Adultreſſes alſo make their husbands to be deſpiſed and of no reputation, though they be honeſt and vertuous men. Theſe and ſuch like innumerable confuſions, ſhame, hurt, hiſhonour, and filthineſſe, follow vpon abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable adultery: beſides the poiſonings, murders, treaſons, manſlaughters, and other miſchiefes that enſue by reaſon of the ſame, which I ouerpaſſe. This did the ancient and noble men of old time weigh &amp; conſider, and therfore righteouſly and vpon iuſt occaſion, haue they appointed the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of death as due for the abhominable ſin of adulterie. Yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterers alledge for their defence, that this rigorous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death appointed by god, hath not bene executed, or put in practize at any time vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the offenders. For <hi>Dauid</hi> was an adulterer (ſay they) and yet receiued no puniſhment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Yea the Lord Chriſt himſelfe, did abrogate and diſſolue the puniſhment of adulterie, forſomuch as he commaunded not the woman taken in adultery, to be put to death,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> but bad her go her way and ſinne no more: and for becauſe no man condemned her, he alſo let her go. To this I anſwere. God hath once alreadie reuealed his will in his lawe, concerning the puniſhment due to this ſinne: now if men do not execute the puniſhment, according to Gods commaundement, yet remaineth the law of God irreuocable and ſure. Therefore this is a vaine obiection. And albeit all ſentences and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that haue beene executed of olde vpon adulterers, be not extant in holy Scripture, it is no maruaile. For Gods booke is not ſo generall a Regiſter, that wee muſt looke to finde in the ſame, the actes and puniſhments of all vnthriftes and brothels, and the execution of all ſuch maleſactours. The ſtorie of <hi>Suſanna</hi> telleth howe it
<pb facs="tcp:19414:35"/>was like to haue gone with her, which plainly ſheweth that ſuch execution was then in vſe. <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo committed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie once in his life, which was the occaſion of the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murther alſo which he committed, ſo that he cauſed not onely his faithfull ſeruant <hi>Vriah,</hi> but other noble men in like maner to be ſlaine. What came of it? Truth it is; he was not ſtoned to death. But what chaunged vnto him? Surely euen as he had diſhonoured another mans childe, ſo ſawe he ſhame vpon his owne children while he liued, and that with great wretchedneſſe. For <hi>Amon</hi> defloured <hi>Thamar</hi> his owne naturall ſiſter: and they both were <hi>Dauids</hi> children. And <hi>Abſhalom</hi> did miſerably ſlay <hi>Amon</hi> his brother for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that wickedneſſe with his ſiſter <hi>Thamar.</hi> Not long after did the ſame <hi>Abſhalom,</hi> driue his owne naturall father <hi>Dauid</hi> out of his Realme, and vnnaturally and ſhamefully lay with his fathers wiues. Whereupon there followed, an horrible great ſlaughter, in the which <hi>Abſhalom</hi> was ſlaine, with many thouſands mo of the common people. Now let euerie man indifferently weigh with himſelfe, whether it be not a leſſe thing, once to haue execution and to die, then to abide the death of ſo manie, and that ſo long, with ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and ſorrow. Therefore was <hi>Dauid</hi> more grieuouſlie puniſhed, then if he had beene but once ſtoned to death. Let euerie man then learne here by this example, that none can eſcape the hande of God, although the worlde lay no hand vpon him. God neuertheleſſe puniſheth, and that with a more heauie iudgement, when hee doth it not here, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth it vnto another worlde. And whereas they make Chriſt a maintainer of adulterers, that is too intollerable wickedneſſe. Chriſt neuer gaue libertie to ſinne: for hee ſayth, <hi>I came not to breake the lawe but to fulfill it.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſayth, <hi>To the righteous there is no lawe giuen, but to the vnrighteous and diſobedient, to wheremongers, to periured, to liers, and blaſphemers.</hi> And to the <hi>Galathians</hi> he ſayth, <hi>Walke ye in the ſpirite, ſo are ye not vnder the lawe.</hi> Therefore, forſomuch as adulterers do walke in the fleſh, and not in the ſpirite, they are vnder the lawe,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:35"/>neither hath the Lord taken the lawe and puniſhment from them. Moreouer, as touching the ſtorie in the 8. chapter of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> we muſt conſider that the Lord ſaid vnto the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultreſſe, <hi>Woman, hath no man condemned thee?</hi> And when ſhe had anſwered, <hi>No man, lord,</hi> He ſayd, <hi>Neither do I condemne thee.</hi> For with this anſwer laid he before her y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of the Iudges, to ſtrike her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, that ſhe might feele and ſee what ſhe had deſerued. But forſomuch as he was not come nowe to giue ſentence as a Iudge but to ſaue, hee woulde not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne her, and therefore neither medled with the law, nor act. The Lord was now come to haue mercie vpon ſinners, and to call to repentance. Therefore ſaid he alſo to this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Go thy way, and ſinne no more.</hi> By which words the Lorde doth warne all ſuch as are tang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> adulterie, to ceaſe from henceforth and to amend. In ſo doing God wil haue mercy vpon them, and take from them the ſame diſhonour, paine, and puniſhment, which they haue greatly deſerued. For God hath no delight in the deſtruction of a poore ſinner, but will rather that they conuert and liue. But if they will not turne, if they will needs be ſtiffe necked, and ſet foorth their ſhameles foreheads: then verily doth God watch ouer their wickedneſſe, and ſayth thus vnto them by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Hieremie, In the deſire of vncleane lust, they are become like vnto stallandes, euery one neieth after his neighbours wife: should I not puniſh this?</hi> Wherefore all they that do perſiſt in this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, may dayly looke for the heauie vengeance of God to fall vpon them. Therefore that thou mayeſt eſchue the ſame, and the contagion of ſo foule a leproſie, embrace theſe fewe leſſons as ſpeciall preſeruatiues.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Eſchew idleneſſe, and euer be occupied in ſome honeſt labour.</item>
               <item>2 Auoyde all occaſions of euill, all ſuſpect houſes, and wanton companie.</item>
               <item>3 Beware of filthie communication, wanton ſongs, and hiſtories of bawderie.</item>
               <item>4 Vſe ſobrietie and temperance, in meat, drinke, ſleepe and apparell.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19414:36"/>
               <item>5 Looke not to narrowly vpon the beautie of a woman.</item>
               <item>6 Be dayly conuerſant with ſuch perſons, as are both chaſte, honeſt, vertuous and godly,</item>
               <item>7 Remember often the paſſions of Chriſt for ſinne.</item>
               <item>8 Conſider the certaintie and ſuddenneſſe of death, and of the day of iudgement.</item>
               <item>9 Vſe dayly, faithfull and feruent prayer vnto God, for the gracious gift of chaſtitie, and of cleanneſſe of heart. So dooing thou ſhalt be ſure to reape the fruit, to thy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall comfort.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The eight Leper, is the <hi>Couetous man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Iches are the gift of God, and are many times beſtowed vppon his children in this worlde in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as may appeare by the examples of <hi>Abraham, Dauid, Iob, Ezechias,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other, who hauing the wiſdome of Gods ſpirit, do know how to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their comfort, for the reliefe of their needy brethren, and to the glorie of God: Contrariwiſe the vngodly doe abuſe their riches to their owne hurt, and alſo to the hurt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note place="margin">Ambr. in Lucum.</note> 
               <hi>Diſcant diuites</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>non in facultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus crimen haberi, ſed in his qui vti neſcinnt. Nam diuitia vt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimenta ſunt improbis, ita bonis ſunt adiumenta vertutis.</hi> That is: Let rich men vnderſtande that there is no fault in riches, but in them which knowe not howe to vſe them. For as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are impediments to wicked men, ſo to good men they are the helpes of vertue. Therefore vngodly rich men may fitlie bee reſembled to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> who was verie rich and mightie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 4.</note> but yet an vncleane Leper. Rich men may offend two wayes: firſt in getting their riches by
<pb facs="tcp:19414:36"/>euill meanes, as by deceyte, briberie, oppreſſion, rapine, and by vſurie: agaynſt the which, the Lord complaineth thus, <hi>In thee haue they taken giftes to ſhedde bloud: thou hast taken vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and increaſe, and thou haſt defrauded thy neighbours by extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>22</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and hast forgotten mee, ſayth the Lorde.</hi> This complaint the Lorde made then of one people onelie, the people of the Iewes: but nowe theſe wickedneſſes through inſatiable couetouſneſſe, hath made a generall deluge, ſo that he may now ſay to the whole worlde, as he ſpake to one nation by the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> ſaying, <hi>They ſell the righteous for ſiluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and the poore for ſhooes.</hi> For couetouſneſſe hath made the lawe, which ſhould be as a ſanctuarie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore oppreſſed, to be a ſnare and a pit for their deſtruction, whereas God in his law hath giuen this commandement to all magiſtrates, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt nor fauour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the rich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuis. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but ſhalt iudge thy neighbour iuſtly.</hi> Againe it is ſayd, <hi>Wrest not the lawe, nor reſpect any mans perſon, neither take rewarde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deus. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes blinde the eyes of the wiſe, and peruert the woordes of the iust.</hi> For this cauſe King <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> when hee had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iudges to execute iuſtice, gaue vnto them this charge. <hi>Take heede what yee doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>for yee execute not the iudgement of man, but of God.</hi> If theſe things were printed in the minds of Magiſtrates and Iudges generally: then ſhoulde not the poore haue cauſe to complaine, as they doe at this day of the oppreſſion which they ſuſtaine at the handes of the mightie, by whom they are ouerborne, and their cauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times not heard, according to equitie and right. Then ſhould neither money, friendſhip, nor affection beare any ſway: then ſhould not iudgement bee turned into gaule,<note place="margin">Amos. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor the fruite of righteouſneſſe into Woormewood. So would they not deuiſe wicked things to keepe men from their right: and ſo ſhoulde they eſcape the wo which the Prophet threatneth. O that they would ſay with <hi>Aristotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> determining a cauſe betweene <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Socrates: Amicus Socrates</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>amicus Plato, ſed magis amica veritas. Socrates</hi> is my friend, <hi>Plato</hi> is my friend, but the truth is more my friend.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:37"/>And as another ſayd, <hi>Nihil poſſum contra veritatem, ſed pro veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> I can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth. O that they would follow <hi>Catos</hi> example, who being required by noblemens letters to be good to an offender, put them into his boſome anſwering the bringer, I will firſt do my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and then read your letters. Such vprightnes of minde without affection, ought to be in Iudges and iuſticers, that they ſhould anſwer vnlawfull ſuters as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> anſwered <hi>Andromache,</hi> making earneſt ſute to him for his ſonne <hi>Aſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anax:</hi> O <hi>Andromache</hi> (ſaith he) thy teares I confeſſe do much moue me, but the teares of my countrey and countrey men do much more moue me, who like enough might periſh if thou ſhouldeſt preuaile. As Iudges ought to be of this vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes taking heede of couetouſnes and corruption by bribes, ſo alſo all lawyers and pleaders of poore mens cauſes muſt alſo take heed that couetouſnes doth not retaine them againſt the truth, that they betray not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of their poore client for any fee, &amp; be ſilent when they ſhould ſpeake. This was a fault imputed to <hi>Demosthenes:</hi> For on a time certaine Ambaſſadours, being ſent into the place where <hi>Demosthenes</hi> ſhould be preſent, and fearing that hee might hinder their ſute, gaue him a large fee to holde his tongue. The day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, when they declared their ambaſſage, <hi>Demeſthenes</hi> feigned himſelfe to haue the Quinſey, a diſeaſe in the throte hindering ſpeach: for the which cauſe againſt the appointed time he ſhould be in publique place, he bound white wooll about his necke to colour the matter of griefe. But a merrie fellow priuie to the match cried out thus, <hi>Demosthenes non an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginam, ſed argenti anginam patitur:</hi> that is, <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> hath no Quinſey, but a ſwelling of pence in his throte. Men ſay that many lawiers in theſe dayes are troubled in like ſort, not with a ſwelling of pence, but of Angels in their throte, whereby they ſet ſilence to ſale. I am well aſſured that there are diuers vpright Iudges, and Lawiers, that feare God, loue truth, execute iuſtice to their power, and do pity the cauſe of the poore, the orphant, and the widow: God increaſe the
<pb facs="tcp:19414:37"/>number: yet this ſhall be no vnneceſſarie admonition for all in generall, <hi>Be ware of couetouſneſſe.</hi> For this is a perillous leproſie, and hath tainted all degrees and calling among men: the which hath ſo long raigned in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it is not only a leproſie, but a leprous dropſie, the nature of which diſeaſe is ſuch, that the more a man is puft vp with that corrupt humor, the more deadly thirſt he hath. Euenſo it may be ſaid of a couetous man, <hi>Auarus non implebitur pecunia:</hi> A couetous man will neuer be ſatisfied with money. For (to allude vnto the woordes of Chriſt) he that drinketh of this water ſhall thirſt againe. Mony to the couetous man is as ſalt water of the which, the more a man drinketh, the more hee thirſteth. And as fire by the laying on of more wood is made more vehement, euenſo the couetous man the more the fornace of his minde is heat with the ſtore of money, the more he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the gaine of riches, of the which deſire, there is no ho, vntil by death his inſatiable fack of couetouſnes doth crack, and till his greedy and dropſie ſoule, doth deſcend into the reſtleſſe flames of hell fire. The couetous man (ſayth Saint <hi>Hierom</hi>) doth euer want, as well that which he hath, as that which he hath not: his minde being more vpon that which he hath not, then vpon that which he hath. Whereas (ſayth <hi>Seneca</hi>) to a contented minde, <hi>Nunquam parum eſt, quod ſatis eſt:</hi> It is neuer little, which is enough: But to the greedie, <hi>Nunquam multum, quod ſatis non eſt:</hi> It is neuer much, which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth not. He which is not content with his eſtate, though he were Lord of all the land, yet is hee miſerable: but hee which is content was borne with great riches. Of all the plagues ſent vpon <hi>Egypt,</hi> that of the flies was one of the moſt troubleſome, for they neuer ſuffered men to reſt, but the more they were beaten off, the more they came vpon them. So of all the miſeries and vexations that God laieth vpon couetous men, this is not the leaſt, to bee tormented with the cares of that, which they eſteeme their greateſt felicitie: and cannot beate them off by any meanes they can deuiſe. They ruſh vpon them in the morning ſo ſoone as they wake,
<pb facs="tcp:19414:38"/>they accompanie them in the day, they forſake them not at night, they follow them to bed, they let them from their ſleepe, afflict them in their dreames: and ſo neuer leaue them till they bring them to an extreame frenſie. For as they which are out of their wittes do not ſee the verie things, but the fantaſies of their paſſion: euen ſo the minde of a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man being once bound in the bands of couetouſneſſe, beleeueth that he hath alwaies golde and ſiluer before his eies, and euer recounteth his gaine and increaſe. But for whome hath the couetous man this exceeding care and vexation? Can he tell? It is like for his poſteritie, for his children, and other of his bloud. Be it ſo. And is not this alſo a madneſſe, for a man to gather together much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for his heire, and to ſpare from himſelfe, as miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men doe at this day? Doe we not ſee, that a large inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, maketh of a friend an enimie? For the more he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, the more he wil reioice at thy death. And yet it may ſo fall out, that he whome the couetous man intendeth to make his heire, ſhall neuer inherit, or poſſeſſe his goodes. Man purpoſeth, but God appointeth heires. According to the ſaying of the prophet <hi>Dauid, Doubtleſſe man walketh in a vaine ſhadowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hee heapeth vp riches, and can not tell who ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them.</hi> If the couetous vſurer, woulde conſider this vncertaine reckoning, hee would be more mercifull to the poore borrower, from whome hee turneth away his face in the time of neede, except hee bee aſſured of ſuch byting intereſt as hee requireth. Whereas God in his worde commaundeth to lende vnto ſuch as are in neede freelie, looking for no increaſe. So vſurie may verie fitlie be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the leproſie, becauſe as the leproſie doth feede of mens fleſh, ſo doth vſurie conſume poore mens goods And the money of the vſurer which a poore man borroweth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on intereſt, is like vnto the biting of a ſerpent. For he which is ſecretly ſtung of a Serpent, goeth quietly to ſleepe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſuſpecting his hurt, and in the pleaſure of his ſleepe dieth: becauſe then the poyſon priuily inuadeth all the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb facs="tcp:19414:38"/>partes: Euen ſo hee which borroweth vpon vſurie, by the delay of time thinketh hee hath receyued a benefite: but vſurie like a priuie theefe inuadeth all his ſubſtaunce, and conuerteth it into debt. This is a monſtrous kinde of deuouring poore men vnawares. The Harpies, the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres, the Canibals, are woonderfull rauenous, but vſurers are more deuouring and cruell then the Eagle that did eate vp <hi>Tantalus</hi> heart. They haue the skinne of the <hi>Hyena,</hi> which (as <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth) will drawe the haire from the skinne of other beaſtes to it: but the skinnes of vſurers are more drawing, for they drawe the skinnes of the poore from the fleſh, and fleſh from the bones, euen to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding of the ioynts and the marrowe of the poore,<note place="margin">Amos <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as it is written in the Prophet <hi>Amos.</hi> The Pike ſo long feedeth on the ſmall fiſhes, that at the laſt hee is eaten himſelfe: euen ſo the oppreſſing vſurer, ſo long maketh a prey of poore men, that at the laſt the Diuell (if he take not heede in time) will make him his prey.</p>
            <p>The verie publicanes among the Iewes were not more infamous and deteſtable, then theſe kinde of men haue beene a long time, and are alſo at this day throughout the worlde: yea in ſome places ſo deteſted, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian buryall hath beene denyed them. As for example: One <hi>Piſistratus</hi> was ſo much abhorred for his oppreſſion by vſurie, that beeing once deade, his bodie was waighed agaynſt the golde which hee left behinde him: which was founde to bee ſixe tymes heauier then his bodie. Which when the men of <hi>Athens</hi> ſawe, they gaue his corps to the beaſts, and to the foules of the aire: and ſuffered not his children to enioy that which hee left, but deuided it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the poore of <hi>Athens,</hi> from whom they were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it had aforetime beene gotten by oppreſſing vſurie. I wiſh therefore all biting vſurers to be admoniſhed in time to forſake their wickednes, condemned by all law of God and man, being contrarie to all Chriſtian charitie, aſſuring them of this, that as the golde whch was gotten at <hi>Toloſſa,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19414:39"/>was the deſtruction of them that got it, ſo their gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which they get by vſurie, will turne to the deſtruction both of their ſoules and bodies. And as the Partrich gathereth the yong which ſhe hath not hatcht; ſo he that getteth riches and not by right (ſaith the Prophet) ſhall leaue them in the midſt of his dayes.<note place="margin">Iere <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> And then what hope hath the hypocrite, when he hath heaped vp riches,<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> if God take away his ſoule. As rich men doe offende in getting their riches by vngodlie meanes, ſo alſo they do offend againſt God in keeping them too greedily, and in hoording them vp, making their money their god: for the which cauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth this kind of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes idolatrie. The Gentiles ſometime worſhipped this frame of heauen and earth, the Sunne and Moone, and other creatures of Gods making: but the couetous man adoreth and worſhippeth that which he hath gotten with his owne hands. And this he doth, becauſe he repoſeth all his truſt in his riches. So that couetouſnes is the thirteenth article of his beliefe. For that which God commandeth he doth not: but that which couetouſnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth, he doth with greedines. If then he be iudged an idolater, which laid but two graines of Incenſe vpon the aultar of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> why ſhould not he be much more condemned for an Idolater, which giueth the whole ſeruice of his life vnto mony. Remember the ſentence of Chriſt, <hi>Ye cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</hi> The conſideration of theſe things moued the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to write vnto <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> thus: <hi>Giue commandement to the rich men of this world not to be high minded, nor to trust in the vncertaintie of their riches.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which ſpeach is alſo expreſſed in another place, when the wiſe man ſaith,<note place="margin">Prouer. <hi>11.</hi> Eccle. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Riches ſhal not profit a man in the day of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Some man is rich by his care and nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardſhip, and then ſaith I haue gotten reſt, and now will I eat continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of my goods:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>11.</hi> Lnke. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>yet he conſidereth not that the time draweth neere that he must leaue all theſe things to other men, and die himſelfe.</hi> Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous rich men are like vnto doues, who ſtill build their neſts there, who both themſelues, and their dammes before them loſt their birds: Euenſo couetous men, lay vp all their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:19414:39"/>here in this worlde, where their forefathers (as they know) left all behind them. But in the day of death and of iudgement, they ſhall crie too late,<note place="margin">Wiſdom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> what hath the pompe of our riches profited vs? At what time it will appeare what a vaine confidence they had in them, which now cannot help when they haue moſt need. Rich men haue ſlept their ſleepe (ſayth the Prophet) and haue found nothing in their hands:<note place="margin">Ppſal. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> that is to ſay. Rich men haue paſſed ouer this life, as men doe paſſe ouer a ſleepe, imagining an aſſurance to themſelues by their great riches; but when they awake at the day of their death, they find that they are vtterly void of all helpe. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof the Prophet <hi>Baruch</hi> asketh this queſtion:<note place="margin">Baruc. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What are they now which heaped vp togither gold and ſiluer, and which made no end of their ſcraping togither.</hi> He anſwereth himſelfe: <hi>They are now rooted out, and gone downe into hell.</hi> Therfore we ſee how dangerous a thing it is for wicked men to haue the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of riches,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note> becauſe thereby they fall into many temptations and ſnares of the diuell, and into many vnprofitable &amp; hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires, which drowne men into deſtruction and perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein they are ſo deepe plunged,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> that with great difficultie (as our Sauiour Chriſt teſtifieth) they ſhal get into the kindome of heauen. Let all rich men then learne this leſſon of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> who plaied the part of a good ſteward, vſing that well, and diſpoſing that faithfully which was by God committed to his truſt. He giueth this counſel, <hi>If riches increaſe ſet not thy heart vpon them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> Whereunto alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth the ſaying of S. <hi>Augustine: Diuitiaſeculares ſi deſunt, non per mala opera querantur in mundo: ſi autem adſunt, per bona opera ſeruentur in coelo.</hi> If thou haue not worldly riches, ſeeke not for them in the world by euill meanes: and if thou haue them, lay them vp by good works in heauen. For of the good and godly rich it is ſaid, <hi>He hath diſperſed and giuen to the poore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>112.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that thoſe things are not rightly called our goods, which we cannot carie away with vs, <hi>Sola miſericordia eſt comes defunctorum,</hi> Dead men carie nothing with them but mer-cie. Whatſoeuer thou haſt beſtowed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, make a
<pb facs="tcp:19414:40"/>ſure account of that to be thine: but whatſoeuer thou haſt beſtowed vpon the world, make thy reckoning that it is loſt, and that thou haſt put it into a bottomleſſe purſe. Diſcreete husbandmen do ſow their graine in the moſt fertile ſoile: In like maner we cannot ſow our worldly ſubſtance in hope to haue a great and plentifull gaine, better then in beſtowing it on the poore. O that we would affoord God ſo much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in heauenly things, as we do to our earthly ſeed. If we want not faith, we wil. Lay not vp then for your ſelues trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in earth, which are ſubiect to many caſualties and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, but lay vp for your ſelues treaſure in heauen, which ſhall endure for euer and euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ninth Leper, is the <hi>Murtherer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Murtherer is pollured with that leproſie, with the which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> curſed <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.</note> ſaying, <hi>Let the bloud fall vpon the heade of Ioab, and on all his fathers houſe: that the houſe of Ioab be neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome that haue running iſſues or leprie, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>Ioab</hi> talking deceitfullie with <hi>Abner</hi> Captaine of the hoſt of Iſrael, ſtabbed him vnder the ſhort ribbes, and killed him. In like maner he had ſlain afore <hi>Amaſa,</hi> Captaine of the armie of Iudah. For the which cauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> before his death, gaue charge to king <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne ſaying, <hi>Thou knowest what Ioab the ſonne of Zeruiah did to mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and what he did to the two captaines of Iſrael whome he ſlue and ſhedde bloud of battaile in peace. Doe therefore according to thy wiſedome, and let thou not his hoare heade, go downe to the graue in peace.</hi> The which commaundement <hi>Salomon</hi> obeyed. For after the death of <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, <hi>Salomon</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that <hi>Ioab</hi> ſhoulde bee ſlaine, ſaying: <hi>His bloud bee vpon his owne heade, for hee ſmote two men more righteous and better then
<pb facs="tcp:19414:40"/>he.</hi> Whereby it may plainely appeare that God will take vengeance vpon all murtherers, who through their priuate grudge and hatred, ſhedde any mans bloud. As it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>He that ſheddeth mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> When wicked <hi>Caine</hi> had ſlaine his innocent brother <hi>Abell,</hi> God ſayde vnto him, <hi>What hast thou done? the voyce of thy brothers bloud cryeth to mee from the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which hath opened her mouth, and hath receyued thy brothers bloud from thy hand. A vagabond and a runnagate ſhalt thou bee vpon the earth.</hi> To the which <hi>Caine</hi> anſwereth, <hi>That the vengeance of God will follow him whetherſoeuer he goeth, and that they which finde him, will kill him. Abimelech</hi> who ſlue his owne brethren,<note place="margin">Iudg. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> had his braine panne ſhortlie after broken with a Milſtone caſt vpon him by a woman, and preſently was diſpatched of the ſmall remainder of his life by his owne page. <hi>Abner</hi> (of whom mention is made before) ſlue <hi>Azahell,</hi> and therefore his bloud, by the iuſt iudgement of God was ſhedde in like manner by <hi>Ioab: Ieſabell</hi> was denoured of Dogges,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.</note> for ſhedding of innocent <hi>Naboths</hi> bloud.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ruben</hi> abhorring bloudſhed, ſayde to his brethren which conſpired <hi>Ioſephs</hi> death, <hi>Shedde not bloud.</hi> For hee knewe that God woulde take vengeance on the ſame: and therefore afterwarde hee put his brethren in minde of his wholeſome admonition,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Warned I you not, ſaying, Sinne not agaynst the childe: and yee would not heare, and nowe his bloud is required.</hi> God will neuer ſuffer murther and cruell bloudſhed of innocents to eſcape without vengeance, though for a time he deferre it. As may alſo appeare by the extreame famine which came vppon the Iewes in the time of king <hi>Dauid:</hi> concerning the which, <hi>Dauid</hi> asking counſaile of the Lorde, receyued this anſwere, <hi>It is for Saul, and for his bloudie houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he ſlue the Gibeonites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Manie mo examples might be brought of the Scriptures, and out of chronicles, and ſtories, to proue &amp; make manifeſt howe the vengeance of God, falleth either firſt or laſt vpon murderers.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> For almightie God hath giuen a law which he wil
<pb facs="tcp:19414:41"/>haue remaine inuiolable, namely, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> The which is the ſecond commandement of the ſecond table, and yet the firſt of the negatiue ſort. By the which commandement the killing of brute beaſts is not reſtrained. Whoſe life or death God hath referred vnto mans will, as appeareth in <hi>Geneſis:</hi> but the killing of man is vtterly forbidden, that no man be ſo hardie as to kill himſelfe or any other. The reaſon is, becauſe man, both as touching the bodie and the ſoule is the moſt excellent creature of God. For albeit he made his bodie of the ſlime of the earth, yet made he his ſoule of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after his owne image,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> placing the ſame in the bodie, when he had breathed into his face the breath of life. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, forſomuch as man is immediatly ſubiect vnto God, therefore God reſerueth vnto himſelfe the power of mans life or death: inſomuch that it is vtterly vnlawfull for one man to kil another, and therefore Chriſt ſaid vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> who had a purpoſe to kill,<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>26</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Put vp thy ſword into thy ſheath: for whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer striketh with the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they which in a iuſt warre, are ſouldiers armed by their prince, to fight for the liberties of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey againſt any forreigne enemie, that ſhal come to inuade the land, are not murtherers in ſhedding their bloud, and in killing ſuch enemies,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25</note> but the Lords ſouldiers fightting the Lords warre, and the Lords battailes: as may appeare by manie teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies out of ſcripture. As when the <hi>Syrian</hi> king had gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his power againſt <hi>Iehoſaphat, Iahaziel</hi> the Leuit being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the holy Ghoſt, came to <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> after hee had made his prayers, and gaue him this incouragement, ſaying; <hi>This is the warre of God, &amp; not of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 20</note> They therfore which fight the Lords battails haue this promiſe made vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God himſelfe,<note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>One of you ſhall chaſe a thouſand: and ten, ten thouſand.</hi> Becauſe the Lord himſelfe (as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh) will teach your hands to fight,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>144.</hi>
               </note> and frame your fingers to the battaile. The ſouldier therefore in this action which fighteth vnder the ſtandard of a Chriſtian prince, for the defence of Gods true religion, againſt idolatrous Papiſts, and proude
<pb facs="tcp:19414:41"/>Spaniards, which with fire and ſworde are readie to inuade, need not to feare and ſtand in doubt: their quarrell is Gods, and therefore vndoubtedly good. Let ſuch therefore take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a good courage, and play the men. The more blood they ſhed of ſuch miſcreants, the more holy are their handes conſecrated vnto the Lorde,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> and the greater bleſſing they ſhall receiue from him. In like maner the magiſtrate, which puniſheth malefactors by death, dooth not offende againſt this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, but doth kill according to the preſcript rule of Gods law, where he ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to liue.</hi> The Iudge himſelfe ſhould ſinne againſt God,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> if he ſhould ſuffer ſuch euill perſons notoriouſly knowne, &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conuented before him, to liue. <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his kingdome, and procured vnto himſelfe the wrath &amp; vengeance of god,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> becauſe he ſlue not thoſe ſinners the <hi>Amalechites.</hi> In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when the Lord had deliuered into the handes of <hi>Achab, Benhadad</hi> the king of <hi>Aſsyria, Achab</hi> entring into league with him, let <hi>Benhadad</hi> go. Then came to him one of the Prophets in the worde of the Lord, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe thou hast deliuered the man worthie of death out of thy hand, thy life ſhall go for his, and thy people for his people.</hi> Which came accordingly to paſſe. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while after he fighting with the <hi>Aſsyrians</hi> was ſlain. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it doth euidently appeare, that magiſtrates doe highly diſpleaſe the maieſtie of God, which puniſh not murtherers and ſuch like malefactors, being therevnto by God called &amp; ordained. For what is the cauſe that many cruel and horrible murthers are committed, but the impunitie of ſuch wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. For murderers many times find friends, which for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney wil procure a pardon. But when through ſuch facilitie of remiſſion &amp; pardon, a ſecond murther by the ſame malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors is committed, what elſe are ſuch friends to bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but buiers and ſellers of bloud? Wheras God to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie hath ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhal take no recompence for the life of the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which is worthy to die, but he ſhal die the death.</hi> Therefore thoſe magiſtrates doe highly pleaſe god, which adminiſter iuſtice againſt ſuch bloody me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the law of God &amp; man.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:42"/>Thus much concerning the letter of the commaundement. <hi>Thouſhalt not kill.</hi> By giuing the which precept, the Lorde is not onely carefull to haue obedience from our hands, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from our hearts and tongues: ſo that both thoughts and words, as well as actions, muſt come vnder ſubiection vnto him, that neither of them be infected with malice, which the Lord ſo hateth and abhorreth. For we muſt interpret the law according to the nature of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law-giuer. Man by reaſon that he onely ſeeth the deed, and cannot diſcerne of the heart, maketh lawes for the outward doings, and puniſheth them alone without proceeding further. But the Lord, who ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the very heart and reignes, maketh lawes for it, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth euen the conſent of heart going againſt his law. For inaſmuch as the Lord hateth the euill it ſelfe, he cannot but abhorre it, whereſoeuer he ſhall find it, whether in hand, heart, or tongue. Of the ſinne of adulterie, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Who ſoeuer beholdeth a woman and lusteth after her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hath alreadie commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adulterie in his heart.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayeth alſo, <hi>Whoſoeuer hateth his brother, is a man-ſlecr.</hi> For as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Quiodit fratrem ſuum, &amp; qui occidit, pari poena digni ſunt.</hi> Hee which killeth, and hee which hateth his brother, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth one and the ſelfe ſame puniſhment. Whereby wee ſee, that not onely groſſe euils, come into reckoning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde, but euen hatred ſetled in the heart, although the hande hath neuer beene ſtretched foorth to execute the ſame. Neither commeth it before him, as ſome trifling thing, which dooth not greatlie diſpleaſe him, but appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth monſtrous, hauing no other ſhape vppon it, nor leſſe account made of it, then of murther. Thus muſt we thinke of hatred conſented vnto in the heart, that it hath a blouddie face in the ſight of the Lorde, and therefore is to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and loathed as the crueltie of murther Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, that the Iewes no leſſe killed Chriſt, then the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans did, although the Iewes layde no violent hands vpon him. Whereunto alſo accordeth Saint <hi>Hierom,</hi> writing vpon <hi>Iſai. Thou</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>hast not killed with the ſword, but thou hast
<pb facs="tcp:19414:42"/>killed with the will.</hi> And God in his law pronounceth a curſe agaynſt this ſecred murther, ſaying: <hi>Curſed is he that ſmiteth his neighbour ſecretly.</hi> Therefore ſayth the Lorde,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart.</hi> Hatred ouerruleth the minde of him whome it poſſeſſeth, ſuffering him not to eate or drinke in reſt, or to doe any good thing, and is alway tempting him to ſlay the partie whome it hateth, and alway enuieth at his proſperitie. It maketh a mans ſoule to growe ſauage, bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth wrath and warre in his thoughts, ſetteth his bloud on fire, driueth him out of his wittes, and ſuffereth not reaſon to beare anie ſway. It disfigureth the face, making men to looke gaſtlie. Yea whatſoeuer an other man dooth, that dooth the hatefull miſlike and abhorre. If a man keepe the lawe of the Lorde, he prayſeth it not: if one feare the Lord and deale righteouſlie, him he loueth not, but diſprayſeth the truth, enuieth him that ordereth his wayes aright, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth backebiting, and loueth ſcornefulneſſe. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hatred hath blinded his minde, he dooth to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour all the miſchiefe he can deuiſe. If a brother offende, by and by he blazeth him abrode, and is haſtie to haue him condemned and puniſhed for his offence. For as loue co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the multitude of ſinnes; ſo hatred openeth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth the moſt ſecrete things. For the ſpirite of hatred through cankred malice and frowardneſſe of heart, dooth worke ioyntly with Sathan in all things, euen to the death and deſtruction of men. Hatred is a falſe reporter, ſpeaking continuallie agaynſt the truth, making a great adoe of ſmall matters, ouerſhadowing the light with darkneſſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſweete ſower, maintaining warre, wrong, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all miſchiefe, and finally filling the heart with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſh poyſon. This is the cauſe why the Lord forbidding hatefull and malicious thoughts in his lawe, would giue it no other name then murther, teaching vs that howſoeuer wee doe nouriſh ſuch thoughts, and make ſmall account of them; yet his iudgement is plaine, that they bee no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then murther, the heart is ſetled in them.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:43"/>The hatred of our brethren is ſo grieuous in his ſight that it ſtaineth and defileth whatſoeuer it toucheth, be it worde or thought, and maketh it ſo heauy that the Lord can no longer beare it. And therefore Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall ſay foole to his brother, ſhalbe worthy to be puniſhed in hel:</hi> ſo much doth he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt words alſo proceeding from hatred. And becauſe words bewray that which lurketh in the heart, and do bring that to light that otherwiſe would not ſo eaſily be eſpied, we muſt keepe ſome good watch ouer them, that from thence we may be led to the priuy chamber of the hart, to ſee how all things go there. For of the abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the hart the mouth ſpeaketh. So that there is no outward thing that can bring vs ſooner to the ſight and ſpeach of the hart, then can the tongue it ſelfe: which, if it be infected with hatred or diſdaine, ſure it is, that all things are not wel at home in the heart. And therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man muſt obſerue the inclination of the heart by the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the tongue, that when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth abrode caſting forth hatred, wrath and debate, we may with ſpeed returne to the fountain, that is the hart, to purge and to clenſe the ſame: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſure that the tongue receiueth all poyſon. If we ſhall preuaile much in ſuppreſſing hatred, both in our heart, tongue and hand, yet is not that all which is here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord in forbidding murther, ment not to ſtay there, but in remouing hatred, his purpoſe was to make way &amp; paſſage for mercifull dealing, towards the life of others, dooing the works of mercy &amp; loue, and wiſhing wel euen to thoſe that are our mortall enemies.<note place="margin">Prou. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> And this is wiſe <hi>Salomons</hi> counſell, <hi>Reioice not thou at the fal of thine enemie, and let not thy heart be glad when he ſtumbleth, least the Lord ſee it, and it diſpleaſe him.</hi> We are all bound to this common rule,<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bleſſe and curſe not. Pray for them which perſecute you.</hi> For, ſo far forth as our enemie is a man, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie it ſelfe requireth, that we bewaile his calamitie. And if this ſeeme a hard matter for vs to do, let vs call to minde, that we are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him who maketh his ſunne to ſhine vpon the good: and vpon the euill: and that we are his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who anſwered his apoſtles, when they required fire from
<pb facs="tcp:19414:43"/>heauen to burne the Samaritans: <hi>Ye know not of whoſe ſpirit ye be:</hi> namely his, <hi>who came not to deſtroy but to ſaue:</hi> his, who healed them that railed vppon him: his, who reſtored vnto <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> his eare, notwithſtanding that hee was one of that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked number which came to take him: his, which both ſaluted the traitour <hi>Iudas</hi> as a friend, and receiued him with a kiſſe: Finally his, which forgaue the wicked theefe, and promiſed him eternall felicitie: which prayed for them that crucified him, and which of his owne accord died for his enemies. It ſhall nothing profite thee to recompence iniuries with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, and taunts with taunts. Thou oughteſt rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the matter vnto God who will be a iuſt iudge, and by no means can be led away from iuſtice. Furthermore, thou muſt know that it is not lawful for thee to ſpeake euil of any man, nor yet to curſe any man. For if we may not do ſo to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, much leſſe ought we to do it to others. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> the more readily to perſwade vs to patience, rehearſeth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modidies which the reproches, &amp; perſecutions of aduerſaries, do commonly bring to the godly. Firſt (ſaith hee) they are a principall helpe for vs to the obtaining of the kingdome of heauen: for Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Bleſſed are they which ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi> And he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men reuile you, and perſecute you, ſpeaking all maner of euill and lying againſt you for my ſake. Be glad and reioyce, for your reward is great in heauen.</hi> Beſide this, they are an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or matter of moſt excellent vertues. For as <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth <hi>Tribulation worketh patience: patience, experience; and experience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hope.</hi> But where is the patience of the Saints, where is there experience, where is their hope, if the wicked enterpriſes of our enemies againſt vs be taken away? Moreouer the glory of God can be by no other meanes highly aduanced, then if we valiantly and couragiouſly behaue our ſelues, in thoſe things which are to be ſuffered for his names ſake. For it is no hard matter to cleaue vnto God, ſo long as all things go proſperouſly and quietly with vs, and according to our harts deſire. But when all maner of aduerſities happen, and yet we
<pb facs="tcp:19414:44"/>conſtantly abide in his obedience, this doubtleſſe commeth of a ſtout and inuincible faith. And for this cauſe, I take it, that Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Iames <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that patience hath a perfite worke: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept peraduenture a man will thus vnderſtand it, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is not in any worke, vnleſſe we perſeuer in the ſame. For when we faint or giue ouer, we acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh not the worke, and ſo without patience it is left vnperfite. Beſide al this, our enemies, by this our conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie are ſo terrified, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further in perſecuting vs. For when they ſee that we are not moued with their iniuries, they thinke that they looſe their labour: and therefore take not ſo great pleaſure of the reproches, where with they haue exerciſed vs. But if they ſhal perceiue vs to be vexed, and to take it in ill part, they will thinke that their iniuries haue taken good ſucceſſe, and will be afterwarde more bolde in their wicked indeuour. This wiſdome was in bleſſed <hi>Iob:</hi> who more grieuouſly wounded his enemies, then they coulde him, by his ſpeeches of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which he vttered to the prayſe of God. For this cauſe <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſayth, <hi>Qui à ſtatu patientiae ante linguarum vulnera cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit: ipſe ſibi teſtis eſt, quod contra manifeſtae gladies perſecutionis non perſiſteret:</hi> That is, Who falleth from patience by the wounds of euill tongues, is a witneſſe vnto himſelfe, that he woulde not ſtande agaynſt the ſwoordes of manifeſt perſecution. Whereas contrariwiſe he that ſuffereth patiently in a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous cauſe hath a promiſe from Chriſt, that he ſhall inherit the kingdome of heauen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The tenth Leper, is the <hi>Murmurer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt leper is the Murmurer, ſuch a one as was <hi>Simon</hi> the Leper,<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> of whom mention is made in the 26. chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew:</hi> who murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both agaynſt Chriſt the patient, and the woman the agent,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> which powred on his head the boxe of oyntment, whch was moſt precious. By which example
<pb facs="tcp:19414:44"/>we learne that there are two ſorts of murmuring: one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, the other agaynſt man. Murmurers agaynſt God, are moued thereunto, either through impaciencie, or elſe through pride, God is grieuouſly offended with this wickedneſſe. For he can in no wiſe abide to be iudged, and reprehended of ignorant men for the gouernement of his owne kingdome and common wealth. And no maruaile, ſeeing nothing can bee done more rightly and profitablie, then that which proceedeth from his moſt wiſe and beſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered diſpoſition and handling. A cunning and very skilfull workeman, holdeth great ſcorne that his workemanſhip which he hath handled and finiſhed with arte and great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, ſhould bee controlled &amp; reprehended by him which hath no maner of skill in that facultie. And thereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this prouerbe, <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam.</hi> Let no man medle with that which is beyond his skill. We are vtterly ignorant of the regiment and diſpoſing of the courſe of the worlde which God hath appointed. We are ignorant of that good which concerneth our ſelues. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord well vnderſtandeth what is moſt meet for vs, &amp; for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore preſume to vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> aboue that which is meet to vnderſtand as we are admoniſhed by the Apoſtle: &amp; let no man take vpon him to ſcan and ſift Gods workes, but rather let him ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, I haue not delt with matters that are to high for me.</hi> Let ignorant man ſtay and content him ſelfe with this, that whatſoeuer is done by God, is done moſt excellently &amp; iuſtly, though mortall men ſee not alwaies the reaſon of al things that are don. It beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs to obey gods will, without curious ſearching &amp; murmuring: knowing that he is a bad ſouldier which followeth his captain grudgingly. But wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues through impaciencie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers occaſions to murmur againſt God. Some do murmur if they haue not ſuch te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perat ſeaſons as they wiſh for: or if they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t any thing of thoſe means which god hath appointed for the ſuſtentation of mans life. Of whom the prophet ſpeaketh thus, <hi>The wicked, if they want meat, will grudge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> This grudging for
<pb facs="tcp:19414:45"/>ſuch wants commeth of vnbeleefe, as may appeare by the examples of the Iſraelites, of whome the Lord complaineth thus:<note place="margin">Num. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>How long will it be before they beleeueme, for all the ſignes that I haue done?</hi> The which were ſo many, ſo great, and ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, that if they had not beene too much troubled and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with a heatheniſh care, they would neuer haue ſaide ſo many times as they did in the wildernes, <hi>What ſhal weeat, or what ſhal we drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. <hi>15.</hi> Exod. <hi>16.</hi> Matt. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but would haue bene much better perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Gods fatherly prouidence for them in their greateſt need. Of this ſort of murmurers, there are too many at this day among vs, who in the time of ſcarcitie, (though in deede the ſame be a plentie in compariſon of that which our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue felt) do more like Pagans then Chriſtians begin to murmur againſt God: bewraying thereby their great vnthankfulneſſe. Theſe murmurers by their grudging ſeeke to make a triall whether God be among them or no, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, and calling for that, whereof they haue no great need. Theſe are not content with <hi>Manna,</hi> but they fall to lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting for Quailes,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and by and by murmur if their appetite be not ſerued. And becauſe they will fulfill the meaſure of their wickednes, they grudge almightie God his true ſeruice, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>We will burne Incenſe to the Queene of heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iore. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as our fathers, Kings and princes were wont to do. For then had we plentie of vittailes, and were well: but ſince we left of ſo to do, we haue had ſcarcitie of all things, and haue beene conſumed with the ſworde and with peſtilence.</hi> Theſe for their wicked murmuring are termed by the holie Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rebels:</hi> and for their wicked rebellion againſt him his vengeance will fall vpon them, and he wil ſuddenly ſweepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away in their deſired fulnes, with meat in their mouths. And he wil vtterly deſtroy them, and their Idols of ſiluer and gold, which they themſelues haue made, and will make them ſo aſhamed of their groſſe idolatry, that they themſelues ſhal caſt away their idols from them into the holes of rockes,<note place="margin">Iſai. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> to hide them from the glory &amp; maieſtie of the Lord. Take heed therefore of this murmuring betimes, that ye grudge not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> leſt he ſhortly deſtroy you with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtroier.
<pb facs="tcp:19414:45"/>Other ſome there are which murmur againſt God, if they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any maner of affliction in this worlde, perſwading them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that the croſſe which they beare is heauier then they haue deſerued, and thereby growe verie impacient, &amp; ſome time diſpaire of releaſe: and therefore ſeeke all they can by vnlawful and bad meanes to helpe and releaſe themſelues. If theſe men were perſwaded of the great good that commeth to the children of god by pacient ſuffering of the croſſe, they would in no caſe murmur, but rather follow the counſel of S.<note place="margin">Iames. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iames,</hi> writing in this maner, <hi>Be pacient brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntill the comming of the Lord: behold the husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it vntill he receiue the former and the latter raine. Be ye alſo patient therefore, and fettle your hearts, for the comming of the Lord drawoth neere. Take, my brethren, the prophets for an example of ſuffering aduerfitie, and of long patience, which haue ſpoken in the name of the Lord. Behold we count them bleſſed which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. Ye haue heard of the pacience of Iob, and haue knowne what ende the Lord wade. For the Lord is very pitifull and mercifull.</hi> And paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Iob</hi> himſelfe teacheth vs the very ſame, ſaying. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom God correcteth: therefore refuſe not thou the chaſtizement of the almightie. For he maketh the wound, and bindeth it vp: he ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and his hands make whole. He ſhall deliuer thee in ſixe troubles, and in the ſeuenth the euill ſhall not touch thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>As ſome murmur agaynſt God onely, ſo other ſome mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur both againſt god and man alſo. Such are they who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur againſt magiſtrates. And theſe are of diuerſe ſorts: as the Anabaptiſts, and Libertines, who perſwade themſelues and others, that it is a diſgrace for a Chriſtian man to ſuffer a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to rule and reigne ouer him. The Papiſts in like ſort, who although they acknowledge the power of magiſtrates and the obedience due vnto them, yet as concerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they murmur at all ciuill power, exempting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the ſame, and chalenge large immunities and priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But the bleſſed Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> exempt no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or degrees of men from the obedience due to kings and princes, as plainly appeareth by their doctrine, namely, wher
<pb facs="tcp:19414:46"/>it is ſaid: <hi>Let euerie ſoule be ſubiect to the authoritie of the bier powers, for there is no power but of God, and the powers that bee are ordained of God: whoſoeuer therefore reſisteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receyue to themſelues damnation. For Princes are not to bee feared for good woorkes, but for euill. Wilt thou then bee without feare of the power? Doe well: ſo ſhalt thou haue prayſe of the ſame. For he is the miniſter of God for thy wealth. But if thou doe euill feare: for hee beareth not the ſworde for nought, for hee is the minister of God to take vengeance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that dooth euill. Wherefore yee must bee ſubiect, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of wrath onelie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but alſo for conſcience ſake. For, for this cauſe alſo pay you tribute: for they are Gods ministers ſerning for the ſame purpoſe.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> (whoſe ſucceſſour the Pope falſely vaunteth himſelfe to bee) teacheth the verie ſame doctrine of obedience, ſaying: <hi>Submit your ſelfe to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ordinance of man for the Lordes ſake: whether it bee vnto the King, as vnto the chiefe heade, eyther vnto Rulers, as vnto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euill dooers, but for the cheriſhing of them that doe well. For ſo is the will of God, that with well dooing, yee may ſtoppe the mouthes of ignorant and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>as free, and not hauing the libertie for a cloake of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe, but euen as the ſeruants of God. Honour all men, loue brotherlie felowſhip, feare God, honour the King.</hi> By theſe places of holie Scriptures, it is moſt manifeſt, that Kings, Queenes and other princes, are ordained of God, are to bee obeyed and honoured of all perſons without exception of anie: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as <hi>Peter</hi> termeth them) chiefe heades, that is ſubiect to no earthlie potentate within their dominions: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> in moſt generall tearmes requireth euerie ſoule to be ſubiect, of what ſexe, calling, or degree ſoeuer he be, to the king, which in earth next vnder God is the chiefe heade. Thereby teaching vs, that as all manner of perſons ought to bee ſubiect, ſo ſuch ſubiects as are murmurers, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, or rebellious agaynſt their ſouereigne, doe diſobey God, and bring vppon themſelues damnation: alſo that the gouernment of Princes is a great bleſſing of God giuen
<pb facs="tcp:19414:46"/>for the common wealth, eſpecially of the good and godlie: for the comfort and cheriſhing of whom, God giueth and ſetteth vp princes: and on the contrarie part, to the feare, and for the puniſhment of the euill and wicked. Yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſhould bee wicked and tyrannous, whom God hath placed ouer vs in authoritie, yet are they to bee obeyed without all murmuring. For the which cauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Iewes by the mouth of the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 27. 2.<hi>King.</hi> 24.</note> to obey <hi>Nebuchadnezer:</hi> and was angrie with <hi>Zedechias</hi> the king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he reuolted from him. <hi>Ieremie</hi> alſo by the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, admoniſhed and exhorted the people, to pray for the health of the king of Babylon. And <hi>Dauid</hi> would not ſtretch foorth his hande agaynſt <hi>Saul</hi> the Lords anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when hee might haue done it without any difficultie, and to his great commoditie. The good and godlie ſort of ſouldiers which ſerued <hi>Iulianus</hi> the Apoſtata, obeyed him in his militarie buſineſſe, neyther did they at any time ſhew themſelues mutinous, notwithſtanding that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually armed. <hi>Phocas</hi> (when hee had ſlaine <hi>Mauritius</hi>) poſſeſſed the Empyre by great violence, and iniuſtice, and wrote vnto <hi>Gregorie</hi> Biſhop of Rome, who obeyed <hi>Phocas</hi> as his Prince, and gaue vnto him great reuerence, If wicked Emperours and Kings, which were tyrants and cruell oppreſſours of their people and ſubiects, are by the commaundement of God to be obeyed, and not onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, but their proſperous eſtate alſo prayed for:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> howe much more are wee bound in conſcience, in reaſon, and in nature, to obey and wiſh well vnto a Chriſtian Prince, our naturall ſouereigne, and moſt gracious gouernour and Queene, without all murmuring, the very roote of rebellion: according to the counſell of moſt wiſe <hi>Salomon, My ſonne feare the lord, and the king, and meddle not with them that are ſeditious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> The firſt Murmurer and ſtirrer vp of ſedition and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, was Lucifer, by creation a bright and glorious Angell, but through his ambicious pride, by which hee was drawen into open rebellion againſt God, hee was caſt
<pb facs="tcp:19414:47"/>downe into hell, and made the moſt foule fiend of eternall darknes. As the diuell (the father of murmurers agaynſt the ordained powers of God) had this foule fall: ſo alſo no doubt all thoſe which are poſſeſſed with the ſame ſpirite, are like to incurre the like vengeance of almightie God: as by reading al ſtories moſt plainly is to be ſeone. Some of the children of Iſrael being murmurers againſt their magiſtrates appointed ouer them by God,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>12.</hi> Num. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> were ſtricken with foule leproſie: many were conſumed with fire ſuddenly ſent from the Lord: ſome time many thouſands of them were deſtroied with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: ſomtime they were ſtung to death with a ſtrange kind of fierie ſerpents: and which is moſt horrible, ſome pricipall men being captaines with their whole bande of murmurers, not dying by any vſuall or naturall death of men, but the carth opening,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> they with their wiues, children, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, were ſwallowed quicke downe into hell. The which are notable examples of perpetuall memorie, teaching all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, how highly god is diſpleaſed with the murmuring and euill ſpeaking of ſubiects againſt their princes: for that as the ſcripture recordeth, their murmuring is not againſt the prince onely,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> but againſt God himſelfe, as appeareth in the booke of <hi>Numbers. How long</hi> (ſayth the Lorde) <hi>ſhall I ſuffer this wicked multitude to murmur agaynst me?</hi> For as Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſayth, <hi>Qui contra ſupra poſitam ſibi potestatem murmurat liquet quod illum redarguit, qui eandem homins potestatem dedid:</hi> Who ſo mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mureth againſt the power which is ſet ouer him, it is plaine that he reproueth God, who hath giuen that power vnto man. Seeing therefore ſuch murmuring is againſt God, let them be well aſſured, that although it be in neuer ſo ſecret a maner, yet he heareth it: for the eare of icalouſie heareth all things,<note place="margin">Wiſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and the noiſe of the grudgings ſhall not be hid. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware then of murmuring which profiteth nothing, and refrain your tongue from euill ſpeaking, for there is no worde ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret that ſhall go for naught. God will make the birds of the aire to bewray them,<note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as teſtifieth <hi>Salomon, Curſe not the king, no not in thy thought, for the foule of the heauen ſhall carie thy voyce, and
<pb facs="tcp:19414:47"/>that which hath wings ſhall declare the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe murmurers, to preuaile the more eaſily in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoliſh purpoſe, and to draw multitudes vnto them, haue euer pretended the common good of al men: bearing the people in hand, that they ſeeke only a reformation of diſorders, and a redreſſe of common wealth matters, as may appeare vnto you by the examples of <hi>Iacke Straw, Wat Tiler, Iacke Shepheard, Tom Miller, Hob Cartar Iack Truman, Iack Cade, Robin of Ridſdale, William with the long beard, Iack Blewbeard, captain Ket, Iack Sharp of Wigmores land,</hi> with the whole rabble of ſuch rakehel rebels, of whom mencion is made in our Engliſh Chronicles, with the examples alſo of ſome dukes, Marqueſes, Earles &amp; lords, whoſe treaſons and rebellions, with their ſhamefull fall and ende, is there recorded, to the infamie and reproch of their names for euer. I ſay, what pretence and colour ſoeuer ſuch haue made ſhew for reformation of Church-matters or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths, their rebellions haue beene the greateſtruine and deſtruction of all common-wealths that might be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. For what other thing can bee looked for to come from ſuch mutinous reformers, their ſtate, perſons and conditions conſidered: who hath euermore beene found to be men of moſt wicked diſpoſition and qualitie: that is to ſay, men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and raſh in al their actions, the greateſt vnthrifts which haue lewdly waſted their owne goods and lands, thoſe that are farre plunged in debt, and ſuch as for robberies, thefts and murthers, dare not in any wel gouerned common welth ſhew their faces, ſuch as are of moſt lewd and wicked beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; life, and all ſuch as cannot, or will not liue in peace, are alwayes moſt readie to murmur, to be factious, to control the ſtate, to moue ſedition, to pull downe and ſet vp, and to runne into open rebellion, or at leaſt to conſpire with ſuch. And are not theſe to be eſteemed meete men (thinke you) to reforme diſorders, &amp; to bring with them a common-wealth to other, who hath ſo ſpoyled and conſumed their owne wealth and ſubſtance? Verie like men to amend other mens actions who haue ſo vile vices, and abhominable conditions
<pb facs="tcp:19414:48"/>themſelues? Yet to creepe into the hearts of the moſt ſimple and ignorant (which euer deſire libertie) they ſpeake againſt the paiment of tributes, ſubſidies, and ſuch like taxes, which appertaine to kings and princes, beating into their heades that it is oppreſſion, and ſo drawe them to murmur and grudge againſt that which is godly and lawfull. For tributes taxes, ſubſidies, and ſuch like cuſtomes, are to be payed for diuerſe cauſes: eſpecially to maintaine and vpholde that roial ſtate which God hath giuen vnto kings and Queenes: ſecondly, that they may bee the better able to defende and maintain vs and the whole common wealth in godly peace and ſecuritie: to preſerue vs from all forraine inuaſions, and from open rapine &amp; violence, which otherwiſe would be ſo outragious, that our goods, our wiues, our daughters, &amp; our liues, would be made common, &amp; commaunded by others. Laſtly, we pay tributs, therby to acknowledge our ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our ſouereigne, who for her good and royall preſeruation, hath power to command vs, our goods, our lands, our liues, and whatſoeuer we haue. For theſe cauſes <hi>Vlpian</hi> calleth tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and cuſtomes the ſinews of the common-wealth, as without which it cannot either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt, or be gouerned. Chriſt himſelf when he liued here on earth, confirmed this, both by his owne example in paying tribute to the Emperour, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in teaching the ſame to be done, ſaying to the <hi>Herodians, Giue vnto Caeſar the things which belong vnto Caeſar.</hi> Therefore ſuch Murmurers as grudge at theſe royall cuſtomes, payed and allowed in all common-wealths, euen from the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, do murmur againſt God himſelfe, againſt his ſonne Chriſt, and againſt the doctrine of his bleſſed Apoſtles, and are like in the ende, not onely to haue that ſame ſucceſſe that <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Theudas</hi> had, who when they vaunted, that they woulde ſet themſelues agaynſt the tyrannie of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, to whome the Iewes payed tribute, and had liued a while by ſpoyle and rapine,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>5.</hi> Ioſeph. lib. <hi>18.</hi> Amtiq.</note> at the laſt turned their owne weapons vppon themſelues, and ſo with their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers were vtterly ouerthrowen: but alſo ſhall vppon
<pb facs="tcp:19414:48"/>themſelues procure the heauie wrath of God, and ſo eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation for euer. So that they which refuſe this law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiection, ſhall not onely make themſelues more bonde, and in the ende ſubiect to great ſlauerie and thraule to forreyners and ſtraungers (according as the Lorde hath threatned, <hi>Thou haſt broken the yokes of woodde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but in ſteade thereof thou ſhalt haue yokes of iron:</hi>) but alſo vndergoe this heauie curſle, <hi>Hee caſt vppon them the fierceneſſe of his anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>indignation, and wrath, and vexation, by the ſending out of euill Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are yet another ſort of murmurers, which grudge at the proſperitie, wealth, and honour of their brethren, the which is occaſioned by enuie. Theſe enuious murmurers may fitlie bee reſembled to the ſwelling Toade, who (as ſome report) can not abide the ſmell of the flouriſhing Vine. And wee finde this true by dayly experience, that thoſe men which by vertue and good deſert are aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to honour in the common wealth, haue many enemies, and are ſo enuyed of ſome, that howe honourablie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue borne themſelues, yet by euill and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tongues are miſreported, and barked at by the woorſt Dogges. And ſome which by true fortitude are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde for the good of their Countrey to deſerue honour, are by one enuious perſon or other that cannot abide to heare little <hi>Dauids</hi> tenne thouſand remembred,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 18.7.</note> holden backe and diſgraced all that may bee. If <hi>Caleb,</hi> which hath vewed the enemies lande be willing to vndertake an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploite, he ſhall bee ſure to haue one enuious murmurer or other, to rayſe vp an ill report to hinder his intent.<note place="margin">Num. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Theſe are like vnto thoſe murmuring labourers, which grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged an equall rewarde to bee giuen to their fellowe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers.<note place="margin">Matt. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> And they play that vnkinde brothers part, which grudged that his father ſhoulde giue his younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> a friendly welcome. They are <hi>Beſib</hi> the diuell, who neuer reioyceth but at other mens harmes. Theſe ſeeke to heale themſelues with another mans wound: the which profiteth
<pb facs="tcp:19414:49"/>them as much, as to gather grapes vpon thornes, and figger, vpon thiſtles. To ſuch the wiſe man ſayth, <hi>Laques peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent, qui oblectantur caſu iustorum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> They that reioyce at the full of the righteous, ſhall be taken in the ſnare. All theſe murmurers whereof I haue ſpoken,<note place="margin">Iude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> are aptly compared to the raging waues of the ſea, becauſe they continally labour to ſome out their owne ſhame. For ſhame and confuſion is the end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Beware then of this, and hearken to the counſaile of the apoſtle. <hi>Peter,</hi> who willeth vs to be harborous without grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, that is,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> to do with heart and good wil, all the good that we are able to performe for our brethren by word and deed. According alſo to the exhortation of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Do all things without murmurings and reaſonings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that ye may be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and pure, and the ſonnes of God without rebuke in the middeſt of a naughtie and croked nation.</hi> This if we doe, we ſhall not onelie eſcape the contagious infection of a moſt dangerous lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but alſo a fearefull ſeparation due to all lepers; as to bee caſt out of our land, as it is befallen the leprous Iewes at this day: and which is worſe, to bee caſt out of the fauour of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. Theſe intollerable plagues, I ſay, we ſhall not onely eſcape, by forſaking our finne and wickedneſſe, and in offering vp to the Lord cleane handes, and pure hearts: but alſo thereby procure vnto our ſelues, and to our poſteritie, the loue, mercie, and benediction of Almightie God for euer: the which he euermore grant vs for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to whome with the holie Ghoſt, be all honour and glorie for euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19414:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
